<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ouija-board</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84028296/1886-04-29/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch+Talking</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE NEW TALKING BOARD.
Many of our readers will still remember
planchette, the strange little heart-shaped
board with a pencil at its point which used
to walk over yards of paper and write no and
of tenie and nonsense if the finger tips of two
persons touched the upper surface of the
board.
Planchetts had Ka day, and mostl died
out But the same mysterious force which
used to impel it it moving now another kind
of little board, and setting whole eommuni
Uet of eminently sober and respectable Ohio
people on their heads.
You see how it it made. A bit of board,
say 18x30 inches, is lettered, rather large,
with the alphabet, A, B, C, D, etc The
letters are put a small distance apart At
the upper corners of the board are written
the words "yes" and "no," the "yes" on tha
left, the "no" oa the right On tha left and
right hand lower corners respectively are
written "good evening and "good night
Underneath tha letters of the alphabet are
the figures in a row, the whole arranged like
thit:
Good-eve.
Good-night
Hen a tiny table it made with four legs.
It is three or four inches high and very thin
and light Two persons tit opposite each
other and take the board upon their knees at
in the picture. The little four-legged table ia
placed upon the board. The two persons
grasp tightly with the thumb and forefinger
the comers of the table that are next to them.
TBS TAXKXJfQ fJOABDb
The two sit down and become quiet, asking
rtioml" After a few minutes the little table
begins to move over the board, It is an In
tel lig nt, or at least, a semi-intelligent force
that guides the table, for it answers
questions. Bomettmes It talks utter nonsense
and again it will write real information.
The table spells out sentences in this way.
When a question is asked, the table moves
towards the tetters, and the foot stops upon
the first one of the sentence to be written out
Then it passes to the next one and the next
and so on, with more or less rapidity, a
gentleman, who hat experimented with the
thing, says: "Sometime the table will cover
two letters with Its feet and then yon hang
on and ask that the foot be moved from the
wrong letter, which will be done,"
One man who tnougnt nit lamiiy was
spending too much time over the talking ma
chine burned it up. Then he left noma on a
Journey. When the talking board could not
be found some one made anotner, ana tne
amusement went on. as before. To tho qu
tion what had become of the other board the
answer was given, "Jack burned It up,
which somewhat astonished Jack on his re
turn.
The questions may be asked mentally, even
by persons sitting in the room several feet
away from the operators, and tha answers
are given Just as readily. Ia some cases re
markable and truthful revelations are said to
have been given about living persons. But it
it not well to girt too much heed to these
revelations.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016373/1890-12-21/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Mysterious+Talking+Wonder+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Ouija: The Wonder of the 19th Century
This most interesting and
mysterious talking board has
awakened great curiosity wher
ever shown.
It surpasses in its results
second sight, mind reading, or
clairvoyance.
It consists of a small table
placed upon a large board con
taining the alphabet and nume
rals. By simply resting the
fingers of two persons upon
the small table it moves, and
to all intents and purposes be
comes a living, sensible thing,
giving intelligent answer to
any questions that can be pro
pounded. Wonderful as this may seem
the "OUIJA" was thoroughly
tested at the United States
Patent Office before the patent
was allowed.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn94052989/1893-11-14/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Weird+Writings+Craze+Unseen+Forces+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WEIRD WRITINGS.
The Planchette Craze Has
Broken Out Again.
UNSEEN FORCES AT WORK.
Some Uncanny Pranks of a Little
Instrument That Once Held the
Attention of the World.
There Is a planchette fever in San Fran
cisco.
Clubs of patient sitters, anxious to hold
communion with the dead and distant liv
ing, have been formed here and in Oak
land. Daily and nightly seances are being
held.
Plancbette is old, so old that it is almost
new again. Early in the fifties the weird
little contrivance was invented and ten
years later nearly the whole civilized world
was teaming with a recital of its wonders.
The most uncanny tales were related of
the marvelous doings of the instrument,
and for a time the greatest scientific minds
of the world were interested iv its queer
pranks. Such men as Tyndall and Faraday
were drawn Into controversies pro and con
over the merits of this occult agency.
Exhaustive essays were written and
learned lectures delivered to prove that
planchette was a fraud and to prove that
planchette's powers were supernatural.
But it all ended where it began. The
deepest study and the most careful analy
sis of the wiles and ways of planchette
developed nothing of scientific value either
to the student of the occult or the natural
forces.
And so the planchette fever died as
quickly as it had grown. Men and women
went back to their workaday world or con
tinued their occult studies unuer different
auspices. Planchette had it« little day nnd
then died a natural death. Or, if it did not
i die entirely, it lapsed into a slate of coma
j from whicn it is only now being resur-
I rected. To-day, in San Fraucisco aud in
j Oakland, and perhaps In other parts of
ihe world, great numbers of men and
women are bent on solving the mysteries
i that still cling to this little contrivance.
And it is all because of that irrepressible
j desire of man to penetrate the mysteries
j of the future. f ,v
What does to-morrow hold for me.
That is the question nearest the heart of
most men to-day. lt is a very part of the
commercial spirit of the age. And as yet
science has made no advances toward
placing the means within reach of answer
ing it. So planchette comes again to fill
the gap between the known and the un
known.
What started the fever no one seems to
i know. 'Hint it has been started and has
already interested hundreds of intelligent
men and women no one doubts, for the evi
dence is clear.
You know what planchette is, do you
j not, and how it operates? Some have
thought there was a hidden secret in its
I construction, but this is wrong. Never
was a wonderful device more simply con
trived; There is first a heart-shaped cedar
board. Pendant from the points of the
angle are little legs with metal or wooden
castors. At the end of the board is an
aperture for the insertion of a lead pencil.
Those who fit to planchette for communi
cations from this world or the next place
a baud each on the surface of the board,
then wait till the "spirit moves." And
the spirit has been moving pretty rapidly
in these parts of the world for the last
few nights. Dire things have been fore
told and timely warnings given.
Ordinarily planchette will write out
what it has to say if time be given i\ but
the quicker way is to write the alphabet
and the simple negative and affirmative on
a large sheet of white paper and let plan
chette spell out its messages by pointing to
tbe letters.
It was this method pursued py a party
of well-known clubmen who began as
i skeptics Friday evening and went home at
I daybreak firmly convinced that there were
i at least many things that they had little
j dreamed of In their phiiosophy. Only two
members of the party placed tbeir hands
on the instrument at one time. The others
j looked on and scoffed.
"We were all unbelievers when we sat
down to that table," said the member of
the party who told the story to a Call
man yesterday. "For a while planchetie
refused to move and we were almost on
the point of giving it up for the night,
when, without un Instant warning, the in
strument gave a sudden jerk and almost
flew from uuder the fingers of Jones and
Smith.
"Roth the men turned pale at this and
in order to rally themselves they accused
each other of having moved the planchette.
On their honor both men denied this, but
since neither had believed his own accusa
tion the denials were useless.
"I think it was a wife or a sister of
Jones that came first. I bave forgotten
the name of the spirit or influence, or
whatever it was, that purported to move
the instrument, but the information it im
parted can be easily verified or disproved
when the next news from Samoa arrives.
"It spelled out 'Apia' first, very clearly
and unhesitatingly. Then it went on to
say that a terrible hurricane would sweep
over the Samoan Islands on the 10th of
November and that two vessels would be
lost In the storm. And touching this
event it would say no more, though we
plied it with queries for a long time.
"Another influence came. I remember
tbe name, but shall not give it.
'Dead or living?' asked Smith.
'Living,' came the answer, but Smith
knew this already, for the name it gave
was the name of his sweetheart.
'What have you to tell me?' queried
Smith, and then he wished he had not,
for the answer that came distressed bim
sorely.
"Twill not marry you,' it spelled out
with painful accuracy.
'Why not?', was the natural question
that followed when Smith had recovered
his presence of mind and bad determined
to face it out.
'Because I like D— letter,' came the
answer.
"Then two men glared at each other for
a moment, for D— sat at the opposite end
of the table waiting bis turn to try plan
chette.^^StHß^^B^o96iQH''SK^
"Now, if It were not already notorious
that D— hail been a little soft on Smith's
sweetheart of late we would have passed
over this little incident as one of the
vagaries of plancbette. But Smith couldn't
take it in this light. He was crushed, and
Invited D— to take his place. 1 needn't
tell you that D— declined the invitation,
but I would stake a small sum that" D—
has his bands on a plancbette this moment.
a,\*'l look Smith's place at the planchette
and presently the' thing began ;to move
again. This time it discarded the use of
the alphabet and gave its message in writ
ing.
"Now, I am not going to place any reli
ance on this thing till I see how it turns
out, but the message that came to me is
Important if it is true.
'"I am an enemy,' it wrote.
'"Are you going to thrash him?' asked
Jone?, who likes to be facetious when
there is the least call for it.
."'No!' said planchette. Then after a
pause it carefully wrote out, '1 am going
to harm him. He is my enemy and I will
be revenged.'
"Well, all this meant nothing without a
name, and no name had been given yet.
Again I asked for the name and ■it not
only wrote oat the name of tbe man who
happens to be smarting under a very just
punishment that i Inflicted upon, him, but
wrote it in bis own handwriting. a
''You should have seen some of the faces
of the men who sal about that table when
they recognized the handwriting. One of
the men who bad laughed loudest and
scoffed the most when we first sat down
found it necessary to go outside for fresh
air." There was no more laughter tbat
evening. i
"Then it came into my bead to ask plan
chette something about itself, but before
we put the questions both Jones and my
self were blindfolded. This precaution is
unnecessary, for it is simply impossible to
move planchette as it does move without
exerting a physical force that would be
readily detected. However, we did this
more to convince ourselves than others.
".'Are you inspired?' asked.
"'Yes,' came the answer.
'By a good power?'
"The instrument fairly flew to the word
'no.'
'By the devil said Jones.
'The devil,' it spelled out without the
least hesitation. s:
'Who are you?' I inquired.
'An agent of the devil,' replied plan
chetie, and this time in writing.
"And after that there was not a man in
the room brave enough to put bis hand on
that instrument."
The above questions and answers can
be vouched for by -more than one man
whose word in the commercial world is as
good as his bond, and many similar dia
logues might be cited to prove— prove
well, to prove that plancbette has a strong
hold on the people of this city once more.
Whether the craze will die out before it
reaches any great proportions again re
mains to be seen.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1915-12-12/ed-1/?sp=33&q=Patience+Worth+Curran+Spirit+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1915-12-11/ed-1/?sp=17&q=Marvelous+Mysterious+Messages+Talking+Patience+Worth+Curran+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Tho oulja board Is coming back
tnto favor and has been taken up
I quit extensively by society women
v In New York, Boston, Chicago, St.
Louis and various parts of the coun
try. Perhaps tho most remarkable le-
Iccnt experiences with it arc those of
Mrs, John Curran of St, Louis. Sho
has been in communication, she says,
with the spirit of Patience Worth, a
woman beliovcd to have existed in
lhe Colonial days and who not only
has sent philosophical axioms that
are characteristic of tho Puritans
but even has gone to tho extent of
sending outlines of plays and es
says and has gone extensively Into
the dictation of poetry. More than
300,000 words havo been received
from this supposed spirit in ihieo
years.
Patience Worth talks In a strange
t English that is archaic and not
J 1 found in the best authors and yet
j may have at one time been the
tongue of Inhabitants of this coun
try. Long condemned by religious as
the direct agency of satan and by
i skeptics as the toy of the supcrsti-
tlous, the ouija board is being ro
f stored to its own former popularity
I through the curiosity of society wo
men. In many parts of the country oo
clety women are devoting their timo
to "communicating" with spirits in
tho other world.
Many sti'ango results of such com
munications are reported and a ao
t clety woman is unhappy indeed if
she hasn't at least one good spirit
i in tho world of mystery who is al
B) ways ready to send a message at her
m, control's pleasure.
Ill Even in staid St. Louis where so-
lit! cIety women arc supposed to bo
1$ very conservative, tho ouija board
il has been, restored to favor whilo
HA
in New York and In various
cities of the east it is quite the
"rage."
In St Louis Mrs. John H. Curran
has gotten into touch with one Pa
tience Worth of Spiritland and has
transcribed more than 300,000 words
thiough the ouija board, all of which
will be published at some future
date.
Patience Worth is believed from
her peculiar choice of words and
phraseology to be a Colonial dame,
who has been wandering about In
space for a long time, burning to
send her messages back to the mun
dane sphere yet finding no source of
communication until Mrs. Curran
bought a ouija board and com
menced taking messages.
THROUGH
CURIOSITY.
The board Avas purchased through
curiosity. There is something fas
cinating about the tales told of tho
little board, whether they be- true
or false. It is known that a num
ber of people have asked the board
to tell them in what land their dead
iclativcs liugercd and were shocked
considerable- when the naughty Utile
hoard spelled out a word starling
A ith an H and ending with an L.
Many have thought that the words
written bv the board were the result
of the mental influences oC the per
son opeiating it. while others have
credited it with supernatural pow
ers. In tho use of tho board at the Cur
ran home, Mrs. Curran always is one
of two whose "hands are on the
board. The latter is arranged on
two wheels and has a pencil at the
end. As the vibration of the fingers
of tho holders develops the pencil
moves over a sheet of paper and
prints numerals o'r letters of the al
phabet, While Mrs. Curran operates tho
board her husband transcribes tho
message as sho reads it to him.
The "Patience Worth" matter be
gan to be transcribed in June, 1913.
Since that time Mrs. Curran has
made public as the products of Pa
tience Worth a six-act play entitled
"Red Wing." a novel called "Tclka"
and numerous verses, essays and
bits of philosiphy.
The quaint language of these writ
ings has probably attracted more at
tention than their literary merit, tho
latter being a matter of some dis
cussion. They are in an antique
language, not the English of Chau
cer, Spenser or any other well-
known classic English writer, but
possibly more like the common
speech of the English people of an
early day.
It is known to travelers that an
antique, almost archaic, form of
English still Is spoken in remote
communities of England. Theie are
districts of England whose inhabi
tants have great difficulty in under
standing or in making themselves
understood by the coster-cockney
class.
Mrs. Curran, however, says sho
has no personal acquaintance with
such speech and that she has not
gone farther in her study of classic
English than other well read per
sons. The language used' by Patience
Worth, she explains, is as strange
to her as It is to others.
Mrs. Curran recently gave to the
Fapyrus Club of St. Louis some of
her messages from Patience Worth,
one of them being a special messago
that Patience had sent the club. It
read:
PATIENCE WORTH'S
MESSAGE.
Good Dames and SIrrahs At the
board thou hast sat and cat of
earth's grow. Aye, and now do ye
cat o' the grow thou knowest not the
looting place of. Yea, thou shalt
hark unto the woid o' MEN, and jet
they do to prate o' DAME. Ayca,
and methlnks 'tis a word aspoke'
amany, that be not the word that
hid 'pon the lung, lest the Dame be
offended I
Aye, then come thou and ait 'bout
the board, and thine cars shall hark
tmto the words o' me, and thou shalt
sec the cloth o' me the hands o' the
loves o' mc did to fashion out for
me. Ayea, I then shall sit me meek,
and thread mc up a bobbins full for
the next o' put.
Ayca, and 'tis frocked that I shall
to be, and nay dame shall see!
Awoe! Nay, this be a piddlc-put-tlng,
good folk!
Athin (within) thy heart shall set
the me o' me at thy go ahence. And
'tis nhope I be 'tis a loving wampth
'twill find. And so dost thou to
smile, 'tis Bweets and love 1 cast
thee. And doth thy heart to shut it
up, lo, then shall I to knock till thou
dost leave me in.
A night o' cheer. A heart o' love!
A God's wish o' loving 'pon thy day.
Anight! Anight!
HOW IT
BEGAN.
Mrs. Curran told her audience of
her first experiences with tho ouija
WW
w
board and of the puzzling messages
received. Later sho used the'board
together with Mrs Emily Grant
Hutchings and began to receive
sentences which foimcd maxims and
philosophical paragrapbs. Then
came the announcement:
"Many moons ago I lived. Patience
Worth, my namo. If thou shalt live
then so shall I. I make my bread by
thy hearth"
The word "bread." Mrs. Currau
later learned, lefeired to the literary
products embodied in the messages.
Mrs. Curran said she would not at
tempt to say whelhcr Patience
Worth was a spirit, but spoko of ,ber
as a beautiful personality, which had
come to seem not a mystery but a
fellowship.
She said the messages came to her
in daylight as well as at night and
that there is no trance connected
with them.
"The words come in sort o a
rhythm," Mrs. Curran explained,
"and I record just what comes
whether I understand it or not."
Pnticuce has been tested by rnoro
than 200 persons and her messages
have never varied. A professor from
the University of Indiana visltod
Mrs. Cunan to investigate her com
munication with Patience Worth.
William Marion' Reedy, editor of
the Mirror, and Caspar Yost, editor
of a SL Louis newspaper, became ac
quainted with Patience Worth and
both declaic her genuine. Yost has
described her as a "spinster of un
certain age; a writer, but a poet by
preference. White the average spirit
stalks dismal and wailing lugubri
ously through the flnito world, Pa
tience comes with a laugh, Yost said.
She remarks. ''I be no sorrj' singer,"
and proves it by many witticisms.
EDITOR
DESCRIBES HER.
Reedy calls Patience's doctrines
Pantelstic.
He describes her as follows: "She
fs a little woman, dressed In gtaj;
with a little bonnet, ribbons coming
down and tied under her chin. There
are lines in her face, not the re
written wrinkles of the smiles or
her youth, but the results of ex
perience Her eyes are biown liico
autumn leaves after a rain. She Is
-between 45 and 50 years old, spright
ly, dainty, delicate.
"Sho has stood beside the stock
ade helping a good man load a gun,
while he defends the settlement
against the savage horde of In
dians." Reedy said the theory was ad
vanced that she was filled in an In
dian massacre and this question was
askcu of her. Sho intimated that
something of this sort had happened
to her and she was asked if she had
not been taken captive oy the In
dians. "Nay, something worse," was her
reply.
'.'She speaks an English almost
pure and undefiled," Reedy said of
her "There is an absence from it
of all the derivatives of France and
Rome, and sho rarely uses a word
of more than two syllables. Her an
swers are- diredt and almost invari
ably in parables. She has respect
for her interlocutor's intelligence."
Reedy said sho is not another
Sappho, or George Elliott, or Mrs.
Humphrey ward nor a Sara Teas
dale,' but rather echoes of all of thct
poets. He said theie runs a consist
ent character through her works and
in two years she has not gotten "out
of chaiactcr." Sho never has used a
modern word or expression and he
illustrated the seeming significance
of this by pointing out how difficult
it would be for a man trained In
Irish or negro dialect to make a 30
minute talk without breaking out of
the character.
"She has nothing lo tell, in my
opinion, "Reedy said, "but she com
mands my admiration and reverence.
She tells nothing- that we have not
heard from tho old masters and
bards."
"What of the divinity of Christ?"
Kcody at one time asked her through
the ouijd board. She answered, "He
bought thee of his loving."
"What of love?" he asked. "Tho
love there is but tho o'er drip of lovo
here" came the respou&c of tho
board.
"Describe tho place where you
are?" sho was asked. "Think you
"Patience Worth," Mythical
Character, Startles Literary
World With Her Quaint I
English In Essays, Plays and H
Novels Noted Writers Are H
Puzzled Over the Output of H
This Woman Supposed to H
Have i Lived 300 Years Ago H
there Is bottom or top; this is a
walless country."
"Can you do anything you want
over there 7" The answer was:
"When you put the will you put the
limit."
"Put" in Patience's vocabulary re
sponds to the modern verb "to do."
"Patience may be a second person
ality of Mrs. Curran," -Reedy sato.
"but she teaches a lovo that is
greater than we can conceive and
that death is the keeper of unknown
redemption."
LITTLE COLONIAL
DAME.
Mrs. Emily Hutchings, who -was
one of the first to receive 'with Mrs.
Curran the messages from Patlenco
Worth, said the first glimmering or
the quaint personality of the little
Colonial dame came in the maxim:
"A busy saw gathereth no rust."
One of the sentiments expressed
by Patience Worth is: "A blighted
bud may hold a sweeter message
than the lovllest flower; for God
hath kissed her wounded heart and
left a promise there."
Of the seances, Mrs. Curran says:
"I sit with a friend, our hands up
on the board, which I havo come to
believe is nothing more than a con
centrator. There is no trance. Ev
erything is quiet with the exception
of Patience Worth. The only
definite part is that while I put my
thoughts awhither, as Patience
would Bay, and immediately the sto
ries, poems, plays., parables, or
whatever her work for the sitting IH
may be, is shown to mo in tiny pic- JH
lures, beautiful and distinct a3 IH
though my eyes saw them.
"The characters move and speak H
and my hands fly over the letters jH
much too fast for me to anticipate- H
even one word. J
"I cannot account for the langu- jH
age. The words seem to be spoken ilH
to me. though I cannot 'say 1 hear llH
them In the sense that we hear tho iH
voice that speaks aloud to us. The H
words come m sort of a rhythm. I lH
am not familiar with old Euglish jH
and yet even the conversations -are H
in this archaic tongue." jH
Psychologists recently havetakcn ,H
up a" study of Mrs. Curran and tho M
Mvstcrlous Patience Worth. Some jM
believe that Paticnco Worth is Mrs. jH
Curran's sub-conscious self. Others jH
have departed in doubt and without jH
expressing an opinion. iH
The ouija board has been con- JH
demned by various religious bodies, iH
but society is taking it up beside il
these prohibitions. The Catholic tl
church has condemned it as a super-
stitlous practice. H
Other religious bodies havo u- H
clarcd that the devil is in hc boaid H
and employs it to send his messages. H
Whatever the truth may be, so-
ciety has gone into the mystery of lH
tho board, not so much with the ob- iH
jeet of definitely deciding if it really jH
is the medium of communication H
with the other world but to,gratlfy H
society's chief attribute Curiosity.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96076839/1920-06-25/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Invented+William+Isaac+Fuld+Baltimore+Dispute+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WHO INVENTED OUIJA
Brothers Ask Baltimore Court to
Settle Dispute.
Brothers, Apparently Lacking Falfh
In Talking Board, Ask Judge
to Decide.
Baltimore. At the moment that the
oulja board, which some years ago ex-
cited the country and then virtually
disappeared, has again come Into the
Umellgbt throughout the world, two
brothers are engaged In litigation here
over the ownership of the patent, t
The trial Is now In progress of the
suit of Isaac Fuld, trading as the
Southern Toy company, who I ask
ing for an Injunction to restrain his
brother, William Fuld, from deriving
pecuniary profits through the sale of
the oulja board.
The plaintiff asserts that In 1904 he
originated, manufactured and placed
upon the market the board under the
copyright name of the oracle 'and
that later William Fuld started the
manufacture of ihe oulja board.
William Fuld asserts that he and
Isaac Fuld were In business together
years ago, and that the oulja board
Is the original talking board, and
claims that tlie oracle talking board
manufactured by Isaac Fuld Is a
copy of the one placed on the market
by him.
The Fulds about 28 years ago were
In charge of a wooden toy factory
known as the Kennard Manufacturing
company, and the oulja board was one
of the devicesthey made to entertain
the young. It quickly won tremen
dous popularity nnd so overshadowed
the business of tho concern that the
plant was largely devoted to the mak
ing of. the oulja board.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1920-01-25/ed-1/?sp=32&q=Baby+Ghost+Spectral+Messages+Curran+Patience+Worth+Talking+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The B?by M tiBeiig Raised bu
4
C
World for tne Daily Guidance of Littl
Wortn Wee Explained by Mrs. John Cu
Says She Was Commanded ty a Spir
Fortn, Find a Certain Infant and A
Spectral Messages from tke Qtner
EvTUL Y -public Ubrary and aU Um book stores hay?
on thiTalr shelves one or more novels by ''Pattereoe
Worth.'' But th?-? is do such living humau be
ioff aa "Patience Worth "?abe is a spook, a spirit, s
ghost, a voice from the world beyond the grave It 1?
daini-ed
These entertaining and ravther well written novels
War? dictated by the spirit of "Patience Worth" to
Mrs. John Curran, of St. Louis, Mra. Curran solemn
ly Ms?trta. Mrs. Curran says aha wrote every word of
that? novels and many poem* on a ouija board word
fttr word as the spectral voice of "Patience Worth"
whiipered them in her ear. t
shit theae spooky novel? ?ire not what this page
deals with to-*lay. ?A nor? oaereet?ng thing to being
done by this spook, .vccortllng to Mra. Curran and
her friends. 'Patience Worth" oommividtTsd Mra.
Curran, who ia childless, to seSarch for a certain rad
head*id, blue eyed infant "with dark linea in than."
whoee father was English and mother waa Scsotoh.
Such a baby waa found and adopted by Mra.
Curran
And thia child, embodying to-day features and
parentage similar to "Patience Worth," who tited 200
years ago, is being brought up by ita spectral god
mother Day by day "Patience Worth" gives Mra.
Curran an ouija board message of advice about little
Patienoe Worth Wee whenever il to U4>?*mI4mL
Three-year-old Patience
Worth Wee, iron* re
cent photograph of tho
ghost-guided lituo ono
ia Forest Park, St.
Louis, She is wearing
tho clothing ordered by
hot "spirit mother."
SIX years ago Mrs. John H Curran, of St. Louis, a
peculiarly healthy-minded, normal young woman,
who is the wife of the former Immigration Commis
sioner of Misitvouri, began for amusement to experiment
with the ouija board. This peculiar instrument for receiv
ing meaaages foom the beyond" consists of a flat wooden
board, about two feet long by one and a half wide, on
which are th? letters of the alphabet, the numerala up to
ten and the words ''Yea," "Mo," "Don't know" and
"Good-by." A little heart-shaped table on three legs is
placed on top of the board. The sitters place the board
upon their knees, the finger tips of both hands lightly upon
the heart-shaped table. After a while an "influence,"
"apirit" or "spook" begins to move the heart-shaped
board, whose narrow end then points to the letters, spell
ing out the words of ?ta* message. A third person, an
observer, acts as amenuensis, taking down the letters as
the pointer indicates them.
The "mestages" are accounted for by non-spiritualista
as an expression of the sub-conscious self of one or both
of the sitters; the mysterious movement of the table is
supposed to be due to unconscious muscle rhythms of the
hands of the sitters.
Whatever the explanation, Mrs. Curran began to hear
from someone who signed herself "Patience Worth" and
who spelled out upon the board sentences in remarkable
English?archaic, a forgotten dialect. This ghostly per
sonage speedily developed into the strongest kind of a
personality. She had been, she wrote, a maiden of Dor
setshire. England, who lived about 1650. She was a
weaver's daughter, an only child. She wrote that "my
thumb is thick from twisting flax" and speaks of deliver
ing fine linen to the "castle folk." Her father left to
come to America, and after the death of her mother.
Patience says she followed him to the new world. ?She
was then thirty-five. Her new home was in the vicinity
of Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket. Near there she
tv a? buried, and now, she says, "a tree grows out of my
grave."
Soon she began to dictate stories and poems with ex
traordinary rapidity and facility. The first book pub
lished was "Patience Worth." The "Sorry Tale," a
story based on the episode of the impenitent thief on Ihe
cross, came out in 1916 and "Hope Trueblood." the last
book, was a story of old England.
The remarkable literary excellence of these writings
attracted widespread attention. Their dialect
passed every teat of experts. It was proven that
Mrs. Curran had no previous knowledge of them,
nor had she the education displayed by the com
munications. Dr. Martin F. Prince, the famous
neurologist, diagnosed Patience "asa sub-conscious
personality of Mrs. Curran and offered to rid her of it
by hypnotism. Mrs. Curran refused to have "Patience"
banished by this means or any other, and scoffs at the
sub conscious theory. Other distinguished scientists
studied her case, but with no better results.
For three years the "ghost" of Patience Worth?or
whatever it is that responda to that nam?2?had been dic
tating to Mrs. Curran by means of the oirija board as a
concentrator. One book had been printed, another waa
on the way to the printer. The first book was already
promising an excellent sale. Reviews had been flattering
and the publie was becoming interested
Then one evening, after the Currans had been' dis
cussing this materialistically agreeable result of the.man
ifestations, Patience Worth exploded a bombshell. In
the quaint old English words which she uses she an
nounced that inasmuch an there "seemed to be some
money in sight." and since it did not belong to the Cur
rans. "but to God," that they should seek "a wee babe
that had nothing, nothing and take it and care for iti"
This was. indeed, disconcerting. The Curran house
was a well-filled one. There was a grandfather, a mother
in-law, a stepdaughter and the husband and wife. Be
sides, they had counted upon using the money for thorn
selves.
Patience, however, was determined and explicit. Sho
caustically called attention to the fact that the emolu
menta of her bock did not belong to those who simply
took down her dictation, but that as the author and main
spring of the volume the returns from it were hers to do
with aa she Dleased.
"I am a weaver of cloth," said Patience on that night,
in the curious imagery she loves to use, "and this cloth
weave is not for him who hath. Thou ehalt seek a wee
one who hath naught, and thou shalt deliver the goods
of me unto it? hands, and ye shalt speak ita name
?Patience Worth."*
This was an order, not a request 1 And to it when the
first shock of surprise had worn off the Currans gladly
bowed.
??L?ook ye.'' the '^heat** went on, "this shall be one
who is sorely in need, mind ye Ye ?hall whisper sweets
unto it. even unto the wee ear that knoweth not thy
words, and tell unto it of a fairy dame who shall minister
unto it and of Him who sent her And she shell be the
love of all who love me and shall smile sweeta unto
them.*'
"But why a girl instead of a boyt" the Currans aaked
anxiously.
"Ye aee,'* answered Patience cryptically enough, "a
man laddie hath man'? cunning, but the wee dame??ah,
I know I"
The Curran? quite naturally asked about the parent
age of the child, ita legitimacy and many other important
things, not the least of which was a description of it so
that they might know when they bad found tbe babe
Patience had in mind
She gave them certain directions???rather vague; told
them "not to mind earth's law but God's"?referring
unquestionably to the matter of parentage and to watch
close if there were any blood taints, but not to go back
further than the grandparent?.. She wanted the child
dressed simply, she concluded, and asked thai "about its
neck thou ?halt hang a sign of Him." The Curran?, and
rightly it, turned out later, construed this to mean
cross."
"Ye shall be upon tbe path! E'en now the wee one
is waiting," she urged.
So the hunt began for a child who wouid answer the
description. The entire "Patience Worth" clan was sent
out on the seareh. Two physicians were selected to ex
amine it when found for blood taint! Much ground wa?
covered in the next month. There were handicaps?an
interesting one the refusal by a certain large St. Louis
foundling institution to allow any baby to be taken from
there because "Mrs. Curran wrote on a ouija board."
During this search "Patience," who seems to have a
strange sense of humor at times, remained silent. Then
one night, according to Mrs. Curran, she directed them
to cease, telling them there was no use in looking for
"one that was not whole," and that in due time certain
signs would be given them whereby they would know
what to do adding that if they did continue it would be
"like a wolf seeking for a fat fowl to feed well upon
when the bird was still in the egg." After this, other
weeks passed by without any reference being made by
"Patience Worth" to the matter.
Then one morning Mrs. Curran met an old friend
whom she had not seen for years, and in the course of a
ride together told some of the details of the quest for the
baby. The friend, in return, told of a young wife who
was about to become a mother, who was practically home
less and friendless, and whose husband had been killed
some time before in a mill accident. That night g mes
sage from "Patience Worth" indicated that at last the
Curraros were on the right track and that which she had
prophesied M'as about to occur.
The next day Mrs. Curran went to see this woman,
who was very ill. A fever of preparation began imme
diately. Layette cradle, perambulator, lawyers, adoption
papers?everything was made ready just as though the
thing were already settled. Seemingly the possibility
that the expected child might be a boy was never for a
moment considered.
The mother-to-be signed the adoption papers, but held
them under the agreement that if she lived she was to
keep the expected child, but that if she died, then the
Currans were to have the baby.
Six weeks later, as Mrs Curran was writing with
"Patience" upon the now well-known "Sorry Tale," the
"ghost" stopped the dictation at exactly nine o'clock.
"This be enough," she wrote, and the board became
quiet.
Everyone was on tip-toe with expectation. It had
been arranged that they should be called by phone at ten
o'clock for news of the birth, which had been imminent
for some hours.
On the hour the telephone rang and word came that a
girl child had been, bom at exactly the moment when
"Patience" had stopped the writing
When the child was seen it had all the marks that
were expected. Its hair was red as "Patience Worth"
had described her own. It had blue eyes with dark lines
in them, like those which -"Patience" had said she pos
sessed when on earth. Its parentage was the same as
"Patience," whose father, she had said, was English and
whose mother was Scotch.
The baby's mother died four days later and the child
was legally adopted by the Currans acting for "Patience
Worth She was christened as Patience Worth Wee
Curran on November 26, 1916, the Rev George Wales
King, a prominent St. Louis minister, officiatine?. Mrs.
Cha?es H. McKee, an equally well-known social leader,
is her godmother, and Casper S. Yost, editor of one of St.
Louis' leading newspapers, is her godfather, with Dr
and Mrs Major E. Woodruff her sponsors.
The "ghost" having thus picked out her child, having
watched over its entrance into this world, having given
all essential directions for its discovery, was it not to be
expected that she would now take a most active part, just
like any real flesh-and-blood mother in bringing it upt
"Patience" soon answered this qnestioft in no un
certain way. It was clear that she intended to have a
finger in every detail?clothing, feeding, education, piny
and all elements of the child's life. And here must be
raised the interesting question of jnst what relationship
"Patience Worth" elsims to tittle Patience Worth Wee
?Curran. Does she assume to be its actual mot her t
Even admitting that there is such a disembodied
entity as "Patience Worth," what possible physical in
fluence could a "ghtMt" of a woman dead, on her own
account, almost three hundred year? </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063381/1920-02-24/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Revelation+Lawsuit+Albert+Yost+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>REVELATION OF OUIJA
FORMS BASIS OF LAW SUIT
Lockport, 111., Feb. 24.An Ouija
board and its uncanny revelations
form the basis of a $10,000 suit here
against Albert Yost. Recently Yost's
home was burglarized. An Ouija
board was consulted to solve the mys
tery surrounding the robbery. Answ
ering the question "Who robbed my
house?" the board is said to have
replied "Frank Walter." Walter is
Yost's neighbor. They have (been
lifelong friends. The board is also
said to have implicated Mrs. Walter.
The board's accusations became
known to Mrs. Walter, who called at
the Yost home. She was told the
Yosts had nothing to retract and
forthwith filed suit for $10,000
against Yosts, alleged slander. The
Yosts deny the charge and insist they
have uttered no word which might be
interpreted as defaming the charac
ter of the Walters.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1920-11-14/ed-1/?sp=70&q=Invades+Britain+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Ouija Board Invades Britain
LONDON, Nov. 10.
THE ouija board has invaded
Britain! It masquerades un?
der the pseudonym of "plan?
chette," but it is the familiar
alphabet and flatiron device that has
helped to while away the tedium of
prohibition in the United States.
And apparently it has landed in
force, because even now officials of
women's clubs are debating as to
whether the planchette is a game,
or, if it isn't, what it is.
"If it is a game." argued one club
secretary, "it should be played as a
game In the cardroom and during
the regulation card hours. As it is,
the planchette enthusiasts are busily
occupied with their favorite pastime
from early morn to dewy eve."
Although she waxed poetic at the
end, it was evident that the official
was really disturbed about the exact
status of the planchette. F->r it is
said that the fascinating business of
receiving messages from the spin*
world?not the s?ance which was w
popular following the war, but the
more informal question-and-answer
of the ouija board?is quite ousting
the card games.
If no regulation planchette is at
hand a substitute, consisting of ?B
ordinary inverted tumbler surround?
ed by cardboard letters, is CtB*
into play. The fingers are pl??*11
upon the bottom of this glass, j^*
as they are upon the little triant"
lar device of the real ouija boaru.
and it skips lightly from one letf*r
to another spelling out its message*.
And the planchette is less ex?
pensive than bridge, because no on*
yet has thought of betting on tM
spirits! </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024827/1922-06-06/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Boards+Sporting+Ouija+Board+Planchette+Alphabet+Witch</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Ouija Boards Are
Sporting Goods,
Rules Court
WASHINGTON, June 5. The
supreme court today announced it
would not determine what fs a oui
ja board.
The question was presented in a
case brought by the Baltimore Talk
ing Board Company, which protest
td against taxation of such boards
as sporting goods, and insisted that
should the court refuse to hold that
the board "is a grade of motor an
toism, involving considerable sub
conscious action of intelligence,"
that it should at least classify the
smaller boards as "children's toys"
The lower federal counts sustain
ed the government's contention
that the boards should be classed
as sporting goods.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/item/sn90050272/1927-12-09/ed-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>She concluded her epic and moodily nodded her head — an Irish Cassandra who had prophesied the evil to come.
"Fiddlesticks!" said Miss Cornelia briskly—more shaken by the recital than she would have admitted. She tried to think of another topic of conversation. "What time is it?" she asked.
Lizzie glanced at the mantel clock. "Half-past ten, Miss Nelly."
Miss Cornelia yawned, a little discontented. She felt as if the last two hours had not been hours but years.
"Miss Dale won’t be home for another half hour," she said reflectively. "And if I have to spend another thirty minutes listening to Lizzie shiver," she thought, "Dale will find me a nervous wreck when she does come home."
She rolled up her knitting and put it back in her sewing bag—there was no sense in continuing work that would have to be ripped out again—and yet she must do something to occupy her thoughts. She raised her head and discovered Lizzie returning toward the alcove stairs with the stealthy tread of a panther. The sight exasperated her.
"Now, Lizzie Allen!" she said sharply, "you forget all that superstitious nonsense and stop looking for ghosts! There’s nothing in that sort of thing." She smiled—she would punish Lizzie for her obdurate foolishness. "Where’s that Ouija board?" she questioned, rising with determination in her eye.
Lizzie shuddered violently. "It’s up there—with a prayer book on it to keep it quiet!" she groaned, jerking her thumb in the direction of the farther bookcase.
"Bring it here!" said Miss Cornelia implacably. Then, as Lizzie still hesitated, "Lizzie!"
Shivering, every movement of her body a conscious protest, Lizzie slowly went over to the bookcase, lifted the prayer book, and took down the Ouija board. Even then, she would not carry it normally, but bore it over to Miss Cornelia at arm's length as if any closer contact would blast her with lightning, her face a comic mask of loathing and repulsion.
She placed the lettered board in Miss Cornelia’s lap with a sigh of relief. "You can do it yourself," she said firmly.
"It takes two, Lizzie Allen." Miss Cornelia's voice was stern—but it was also amused.
Lizzie groaned, but she knew her mistress. She obeyed. "I’ve been working for you for twenty years," she muttered. "I’ve been your girl for twenty years, and I’ve got a right to speak my mind."
Miss Cornelia cut her off. "You haven’t got a mind. Sit down," she commanded.
Lizzie sat, her hands at her sides, with a sigh of tried patience. Miss Cornelia put her unwilling fingers on the little moving table that is used to point to the letters on the board. She placed her own hands on it, too, along with Lizzie's.
"Now, make your mind a blank," she commanded.
"You just said I haven’t got any mind," complained Lizzie.
"Well," said Miss Cornelia magnanimously, "make what you haven't got a blank."
The repartee silenced Lizzie for the moment—but only for the moment. As soon as Miss Cornelia had settled herself comfortably and tried to make her mind a suitable receiving station for messages, Lizzie began to mumble the sorrows of her heart.
"I stood by you through thick and thin," she mourned in a low voice. "I stood by you when you were a theosophist—anti-Catholicism, fletcherism, and rheumatism—but when it comes to carrying on with ghosts—"
"Be still!" ordered Miss Cornelia. "Nothing will come if you keep chattering."
"That’s why I’m chattering!" said Lizzie, driven to the wall. "My teeth are, too," she added. "I can hardly keep my upper set in," and a desolate clicking of artificial molars attested to the truth of the remark.
Then, to Miss Cornelia’s relief, she was silent for nearly two minutes, only to start so violently at the end of the time that she nearly upset the Ouija board on her mistress' toes.
"I’ve got a queer feeling in my fingers—" she whispered in awed accents, wriggling her arms violently.
"Hush!" said Miss Cornelia indignantly. Lizzie always exaggerated, of course—but now her own fingers felt prickly—uncanny. There was a little pause while both sat tense, staring at the board.
"Now, Ouija," said Miss Cornelia defiantly, "is Lizzie Allen right about this house, or is it all stuff and nonsense?"
The pointer moved—slowly at first, then quicker. Both stared at it, transfixed. It stopped.
"That’s queer," Miss Cornelia said, with a forced laugh. She looked at Lizzie, still worried. "I wonder what it means?"</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/item/sn89066315/1920-03-09/ed-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>That thousands, upon thousands of
intelligent persons in this supposedly
cultured and rational nation of ours
should, become believers in such a
practice as. the so-called automatic
writlngbytho use of the ouija board,
seems hard, to believe. But it's true,
nevertheless.
Thoughts brought out by the ouija
board or any other form of automatic
writing are easily explained, being
r.imply the recurrence to the mind of
past events or ideas, or else new
thoughts built up by the imagination.
'By intense concentration it is passi
ble for one to call to mind facts which
he may have learned in the past in a
somewhat passive manner, the in
formation having been gained when,
his attention being focused on some
other matter, he was practically un
aware of its entry.
Ye,t persons have been so wrought
up over the the workings of the
board that thcy hate suffered nervous
breakdowns, some even having been
declared insare after having indulged
in long seances with the ouija board.
The desire for this sort of psychic
experiment hju hi, a number of towns
almost like an epidemic. Every man,
woman and child In El Cerrito, Cal.,
will be examined by. alienists because
there Is now an ouija craze in the
town. Seven ol its Inhabitants have
already been &djndged insane.
Even if automatism were of any
value, it would never be worth risk
ing the equilibrium of the Intellect
The dangerous fad must be checked.
To persons cf a marked degree of
Many of these rumors are legitimate,
but there are often those that are
circulated to injure this or that stu
dent candidate, with no word of truth
in their content</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/item/sn83045085/1920-04-05/ed-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>OUIJA SO SAID
o-- U
The recruit hought a ouija board
For ninety-seven cents;
His faith ill spirit lore was firm,
His interest intense.
Hle placed his paws upon the scroll
And asked a question, sic-
"I get my big league trial next month.
Now, tell me, will I stick'
The good old ouija answered "Yes,
You'll win a real star's place,'
Which caused a seraph's smile to
spread
Across the rookie's face.
"I know that I'll make good," he said,
Unto his big league boss.
"I care not what the ouija says,
Young ilnal, bu t understalld,"
The chief remallrked, "I do Ilot care
What ghosts lend you a hand.
I care not if old Hercules
Should try to help you bat,
Nor Mercury himself should make
You run ten seconds flat,
Provided other defunct guys
Who've gone beyond the brink
l)on't hang around the ouija board
And teach you how to drink.
I donii't want Croesus butting in
To nlake you grab the kale,
Nor slick Adonis luring you
To. chase some Texas frail,
Some ghosts are good, I will admit
While other ghosts are nix;
You'd ibet depend upon yourself
Or linger in the sticks."
-Seattle Union-Record.
Bulletin Want Ads Bring
Results.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/item/sn86092523/1892-06-19/ed-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>At the beginning of the holiday sea*
son last year a new toy called “oulja*
was introduced to the public. It was
believed that it might amuse small gath
erings for a season and tben be cast
aside and forgotten. It sold fairly well,
but, lo tha.turprise of the dealers, the
sales did not fall off after the holiday
season. The manufacturers were called
upon to put forth extra efforts to sup
ply the unexpected demand. They be
lieved that they had hit the popular
fancy in much the same way as the
originators of ‘‘Pigs in Clover” had.
After a while, however, the sales fell off
gradually, although some are sold yet.
The retailers reported after the holi
days that a new use had been found for
the ouija. I he
spiritualists had
seized upon it as
an excellent sub
stitute for the
planchette, they
said, and what
ori.JA or espirito. had been intend
ed to be only a plaything for idle hours
became a medium for communications
between believers and alleged inhabit
ants of the “spirit world.” Since the
beginning of the year the ouija has been
used at many gatherings of Spiritual
ists. m New England, and in Boston
especially, the use of the ouija has be
come almost a craze among the believ
ers, and wonderful stories are told of its
effectiveness as a communicating medi
um between the living and the dead.
According to some of the enthusiasts
the spirits have taken to the ouija with
marvelous zeal. Apparently they have
been waiting for it, in order to give true
believers their views on various sub
jects. In fact, the reporter was assured
solemnly by one devotee that the ouija
had really been invented by certain
spirits of departed geniuses, who there
after communicated their idea to the
mortal who, as their instrument, re
vealed It to the living world. These
facts, said the reporter’s informant,
were directly communicated to a gath
ering of spiritualists in this city
through the medium of the ouija. The
message received on that occasion was to
the effect that the spirits, knowing that
the planchette no longer had the confi
dence of the public, bocause of the de
ceptions practised by unscrupulous
mediums, had decided upon this new
idea, which contained many of the
best features of the planchette.
In fact, the difference between the
two Is chiefly in details; the theory is
practically the same. The planchette
consisted of. a
heart- shaped
board with two
little wheels un
der the lari?e end
to enable the spir
its to move it
easily. Under the TnEplanchktte.
pointed end was a pencil by means of
which the supposed spirits wrote mes
sages to their living friends. Usually
the board was about six inches in length
and about four inches in width. Occa
sionally, though not often, it varied
slightly from the*|heart shape. The
upper surface was polished usually.
Some times the wheels were little metal
easters, and at other times they were
wooden wheels. In either case, they
were made so that tho board could be
wheeled easily in any direction. The
pencil could be of lead, in which case
the writing was done on paper, or of
slate, when the message was written on
a school slate.
OUIJA BOAHD.
Two persons operated the plauchette,
under the supposed influence of the
spirits. The planchette was placed on
paper, and the living operators sat on
opposite sides of it, each one resting
the flnger9 of both hands lightly on
the polished surface. The messages
were received in various ways. Some
times one of the two would ask ques
tions, either aloud or mentally, and
wait until spirits moved the other to
record the answer. Sometimes neither
one spoke, but waited silently for the
spirits to manifest themselves un
bidden. Many curious results have
been recorded. Bishop Montagu and
other mind readers asserted that it was
possible for a strong mind to dominate
a weaker one so as to make the latter
write messages that the former bad dic
tated mentally. Of course, a prerequi
site in this, as In all similar trials, was
that both operators should fasten their
minds intently upon the questions
asked. The messages were written in
all kinds of ways—upside down, hori
zontally, vertically, butrarely with uni
formity. Sometimes the questions were
asked by others in the party or written
by them on pieces of paper, which were
concealed afterward. The planchette
created a great furor, but the exposures
of unscrupulous operators destroyed the
popular interest in it, although Spirit
ualists generally yet give it credence.
The ouija is very similar, but no writ
ing is done with it. The ouija is a
heart-shaped board of about the same
size as the planchette. Instead of
wheels or castors, it is supported on
three little legs, two at the large end
and one at the point, with little pieces
of felt at the ends. The ouija is placed
od the polished surface of a board
about two feet in length and one foot in
width. The letters of the alphabet and
the words Yes and No are painted on
the board. The operators sit on oppo
site sides of the board, with their Angers
resting slightly on the ouija. The point
of the latter is the indicator. It may
move backward, forward, or laterally to
any letter or word on the board.
Some say that there is less chance of
fraud with the ouija than with the plan
cbette, while others maintain the oppo
site. Those who have faith in it tell
marvelous stories of the operations of
the ouija. They say that intricate ques
tions, prepared by strangers, to the op
erators, and known only to the former,
have been answered correctly and rap
idly.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/item/sn86092523/1892-06-19/ed-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>OUIJA.
WISH I were a ouija board
And some rank profiteer
Would ask me where to place his
hoard,
I’d tell him, never fear!
I'd recommend some oil well stocks,
Which soon would rake him on the
rocks.
i
I wish I were a ouija board
And when the day was spent,
I’d loose some pleasant words I've
stored
For him who jumped my rent.
I’d tell the Shylock-shocking thief
That of all robbers he is chief!
(I’d tell him in the flesh, but then I
The cuss might boost my rent again.)
I wish I were a outja board,
I’d hand it to the boss,
And though his name were Schwab
or Ford,
I’d tell him “C-o-m-e a—r-o-s-s-!”
I’d name the sum I’d like to earn
To even up my tax return.
I wish I ran a ouija joint
And then when Woodrow came
And asked me whom he should ap- I
point,
I’d indicate a name.
And if the name were mine—oh,
well,
That name I know best how to spell. I
I’d also hint a mild desire
Concerning some he still might fire.
I wish I were —and you would see
When some big mutt should come
And lay his loutish hands on me,
I’d be both deaf and dumb.
Or I might be induced to tell
In three short words where he might
dwell.
But if some dainty-fingered miss</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>



  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-electric-chair</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032490/1887-04-17/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Death+Dynamo+Electric+Chair+Capital+Punishment</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>DEATII Ef THE DYNAMO.
THE HANGMAN AND HIS GALLOWS
RELICS OF BARBARISM.
Dr. Smilhwick Discourses of a Moro Hu
mane Agent for tho Infliction of Cap
ital Punishment Description of Ills
Deadly Electric Chair.
Dr. A. P. Southwick, who is a member of
tho commission to ascertain the most
humano and practical method known to
modern science for carrying tho death sen
tence into effect in capital cases, is an enthu
siastic investigator, and since tho commis
sion was created by tho last legislature ho
has spent considerable time in making re
searches. "Do you believe in capital punishment,
doctor?" was asked.
"I believe tho death penalty is necessary,"
ho replied, "for there is a class of people, a
lower order of beings, to whom it is positive
ly necessary. I refer to peoplo who como
from a lino of murderers that is, men who
havo descended directly from families of
criminal proclivities. Tho man who walks
around ready to commit a willful, premedi
tated murder should die. He belongs to a
race that we want to wipo from tho face of
the earth. The laws are liberal enough, with
the various degrees of homicido and man
slaughter, to protect individuals who do it in
the heat of passion or under intense provo
cation." "And about women?"
"If the law i3 changed from hanging to
death by electricity then it should and
would bo made to include women as well as
men. Any discrimination between the sexes
would make the law unconstitutional."
""Would there b3 any objection to execut
ing women with electricity.'"
"No, sir; there would not. I think there
would no longer be tho samo prejudico that
thcro is now, because Imaging is a poor way
of inflicting the death penalty."
"How would you uso electricity?"
"Just seo here," said Dr. Southwick,
jumping up and .seating himself, in an arm
chair. "Tho condemned man cansifc natur
ally in a chair like this, placo his liands on
the metal arms and converse with those
around him. Tho metal plates would ba
connected with a powerful d3namo and at
tho proper moment somebody in another
room would press a button, closo tho current
and tho fatal shock would pass through tho
body of the subject. Tho chargo would go
straight through tho heart and lungs and
penetrate the system, death instantly result
ing. Tho expense of the apparatus with which
to execute by electricity ia this city would
bo about $150. Connection cculd bo made
with the electric light station, and tho ex
pense of an execution thereafter would bo of
littlo consequence. It would not cost any
more than a cigar to kill a condemned man
after that. It would not bo necessary to
maintain extensive and powerful machinery
in nil tho prisons, anil it would bo vastly
cheaper than hanging."
"You believe then in electricity?'
"Electricity Ls tho coming power. Death
is instantaneous and tho body i not defaced.
There is not tho morbidness of n hanging,
which is a relic cf barbarism. Just seo a
recent execution here Heman's I think it
was when tho hanged man breathed fifteen
minutes afteV the drop fell. If that is in
stantaneous death then I would rather havo
u lingering death."
"Have you considered jwisons as a means
of executing criminals''
"Prussic acid has been raggested, but
neither that nor garroting has met with any
favor. A few havo advocated tho guillotine,
but I thin!; it is a barbarous mode of causing
death. Hardly any one favors hanging in
preference to electricity, tho very system
being barbarous as are tlio method and
paraphernalia used.'
"Do you expect t!:at your plan wul be
adopted'"
"I sincerely hope i; w3L If it L adoptdl
by the coming legislarare otlxr slates will
undoubted!- adopi it, and I tiisk that
within two years it will bo adopted all over
the world- It wooll certainly L-j better
than obliterating the death penalty, and m
tho case of a woman there would b; much
less objection to its operation than there is
to hanging."
Dr. Soulhw'ci added that in England the
eamo quesuon had arisen, but no satisfactory
substitute for hanging had bsen suggested.
One of tho commissioners suggested that
various means bo adopted and the condemned
culprit 1x3 given his choice of deaths.
State Senator Daniel II. Meridian has
written a letter to the commission in which he
saj-s: "Tho principal objection to the present
inothod is that it Li primitive in its origin
and barbarous hi its effects. It lacks every
element of exactness and precision. It i3
absolute!' impossible to arrango a formula
as to the size of tho rope, tho longth of the
drop or the h"ft of the weight and the dis
tanco of its fall, as theso sc-vcral elements
must not only depend upon tho sizo and
weight but tho general buiid and make up ot
tho convict. Tho want of exactness in these
several elements sometimes leads to the muti
lation of tho bodv by severing the head; to
unnecessary and sevcro suffering by reason
of tho breaking of the rop?, nnd also to death
by sufTocal .en whero there has been an im
proper aijustment. All these things com
bine to luako hanging by the neck most
brutal.
"I am heartily in favor of the application
of electricity for tho purposes in question,
for the reason that it is simple, sure and
painless. 1 think that if the places of execu
tion wero limited to two in this state, say
ono at Auburn and ono at Sing Sing, the
two stato prisons, and that all convicts as
Foon as condemned to suffer tho death
penalty should bo confined in ono of those
two prisons (depending somewhat upon the
locality of tho trial), it would be a vast im
provement upon tho present method of hav
ing tho criminal confined in the county jail
till the daj- of execution."
Regarding tho machinery to Iw used
Senator llcl.lillan says: "Theso 'executions
could take place in tho jail proper, in a room
set apart for that purpose, with no appli
ances save that of a chair, with tuo nana
rest of each arm properly connected with
an electric machine, in which tho condemned
might bo seated and tho connection made by
strapping a hand to the hand rest on each
chair. There can bo no difficulty whatever
in procuring a current of electricity of suffi
cient strength to paralyze tho muscles of
tho heart by this method. Indeed, tho cur
rent that is used in this city for electric
lighting purposes is of sufficient strength to
absolutely dismember the body of nay human
being, but a current of electricity of suffi
cient strength to cause instantaneous death
by passing from hand to hand through the
heart wi'l not mark the body in tho least."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86075267/1888-12-13/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Electrical+Electric+Chair+Capital+Punishment+Killing+Electricity+murderers+lightning</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>APTAN PROPOSED.
gow Will Electrical Execu
tions Be Accomplished?
TlE LAST THING IN KILLING.
How Various Nations Do Their Criminals
to Death--New TYok State the Flrat
commeunty to Adapt the Newest Thing
in Capital PlUnihment.
After Jan. 1, 1880, murderers in New York
sate will depart this life on a streak of light
ing. Any man who has been sentenced to
death will go off. so quick that he won't
know anything about it. The subject of
putting murderers to death by electricity has
been agitated in the Empire state for more
than a year.
After mature deliberation it was concluded
that hanging would have to go.
Hanging has been the fashionable mode of
punishment for centuries, but a commission
*appointed by Governor Hill concluded that it
was too harrowing. They made a number
of experiments, and finally decided upon
electricity. A bill was passed by the legis
lature, but-no provision was made as to the
way the fluid was to be applied. Finally the
Medico-legal society took the matter Uo, ap
pointed a commission, and the result was
that a particular form of applying the elec
tricity was suggested. This way of killing
off the refuse population will probably be
used in New York state hereafter. Three
ways of applying the fatal electricity were
proposed, but none of them answered the
purpose. One was passing the electri.
iots city from wrist to
wrist through the
body, another
was passing the
current from the
head to one of the
wrists, the third
Swas topassthecmu
rent completely
t through the prison.
S1 etr's body from head
to foot.
c c m The objections to
A CURRENT IN THE BRAIn these methods were
that the prisoner might have convulsions.
It was desired, of course, to take the utmost
care of the prisoner. He was to die as pleas
antly as possible. Then the attendant under
this method might make a mistake and be
struck himself.
The commission finally concluded that the
best way would be to have the current pass
through the hoad from the top to the back of
the neck. One electrode is fitted to the top
of the prisoner's head, another placed in con
tact with the small of his back. The top
electrode connects with the positive pole, the
bottom with the negative pole. A leathern
rest holds the prisoner's head and bands
keep him from moving. The current, in go
ing from one electrode to another, does not
keep in a straight line, but spreads out and
goes through the entire brain. It resembles
somewhat a bundle of faggots tied at the two
ends and swelling out in the middle. The seat
of consciousness being in the brain, and the
headquarters for all the nerves being located
there, it is of course as plain as day that,
when an electro-motive force of 8, 30 volts
is applied, the prisoner is bound to die. The
great beauty of this system is that the pris
oners don't know it either.
Heroe we have a villain who is too bad to
stay around and commit murder any more.
Step up, ladies and gentlemen, and gazoon
the wayitisdone. Here we have astouttable
covered with rubber cloth and having holes
around its borders for binding. Prisoner,
come up here and lieon the table. Attendant,
bind the prisoner to the table. Here is an
electrode (the negative one) which comes up
through the table and touches the small of
the prisoner's back. Here we have a helmet,
to which the other electrode is joined, and
t helmet is put on the prisoner's head. The
Wtrode now touches the top of the prison
9~head, which has been moistened bywarm
ater. Prisoner, are you ready? Then, let
'cgo, Gallagher, and the thing is done. The
man is as dead as a
door nail. Another
modification of this
method is to let the
prisoner sit in a
chair. Some pris
oners will undoubt
edly prefer to sit
in a chair, whleilo
others who were
born tired will pro- e'O
for to lie at full
length. Eerthinug THE DEATH APPARATUS.
will be done in regard to the com ort of the
prisoners, and their taste will be consulted
in every particular.
This, in brief, is the way the prisoners will
"lick the bucket" after the 1st of January.
When Elbridgo T. Gerry, Mathew Hale
and Alfred P. Southwick wero appointed last
winter to investigate the matter they took
the trouble to look up the various methods of
Panishment in different countries.
E RLY MODES OF EXECUTION.
Hanging is a very old institution. The
earliest form of the gallows was undoubtedly
a ltout tree and a convenient limb, and they
seem to have retained their popularity ever
sinae the hanging of Ai by Joshua, as re
corded in the Bible.
Hanging was used and known by the Eng
lish In the Thirteenth century. They proba
bly got it front the French. It is recorded
by a French historian in 1242 that a knight,
ho had been judicially put to death, was
hungon the gibbet after the breath had left
his body. The first use of the primitive gal
lows seems to have been to exhibit the body
afler death. The first gibbet used in Eng
and to expose criminals was in the reign of
Henry III. The first to be executed by the
rP was Earl Ferrers, May 5, 1760. After
is ams had been secured by a black sash
an a common halter passed around his neck,
lamonnted a part of the scaffold eighteen
i.ches above the rest, and the signal being
given by the sheriff that part of the floor
ank under him to a level with the rest, and
be remained with nothing to stand on.
It seems to be fairly settled that sensation,
reection and mental horror accompany the
physicsl tortures of those who are in the act
tbstangulating. Examples are frequent of
ao who commit suicide by hanging at
tmpting to regain their foothold, finding
te tortures of strangulation greater than
tbey had conceived It is reported of a
Onman, executed in 1160, "that the rope
ilped her cap partially from her face, and
ghile hanging at the halter's end, by a
mighty effort she pu up one of her hands
ldaiently totdraw it down again over her
dist0rted features."
S IETHODS NOW LV USE.
Here ar Some cf the different methods of
tSecating criminals:
Auto da fe, or execution by the Spanish Inqunlsl
usally by burning.
rci ith clubs, practiced by the South
Behediagor decapitation, known to the Greeks,
soms and Jewrs, and used formerly in England
le ice, onl.nfw in China and ,Taponu.
ng from cannon, employed m quelling a
ios among the Sepoys In India.
ao .ormerly used in England in the case of
oan the familiar mode of execution in the
early religioas perseentions.
fag. ali.e, elployed among barbarous tribes
t ze id countries.
?aion, a very ancient form of executlon.
ýe eeonb employed by military tribunals
r tenth4a man was chosen by lot to die Is
itw era llarge number of soldiers mutinied.
tebeIs~.t or bisecting, mentioned in the Bible
sItten men were sawn asunder.
[l __.heiboment, used in France in the Seven
nla~sOicogu0 in ancient syria, Greece
eeanwild breasts, an ancient punishment
(nuelt, used in Englssia.
l with the knout, used In Russia.
i rroting a punishment Originally devised by
the rab and eoors mi
Thegullouine, hari-kar, Imps emeno, polsening,
lhnging poundings Ia a motar, precipitation,
pressing to death t ck, rnning the g tet,
featio emae th e i
reader that any one of these methods might
be improved upon sossiblefar as the phyical com t
fort of the victi in concerned In countrise
where these modes of punishment were and
in some cases are now practiced, the main ob
ject was to give the prisoner as much soffer
ing as possible. ie was held up as a terrible
example. Now, however, the main object in
to get the prisoner out of the way as soon as
possible. In order to understand how quick
a man can die under the force of electricity,
let us consider first how fast a man can think.
Well, it takes just one-tenth of a second fora
nerve to communicate with the brain, ac
cording to Professor Hemholz Now Pro
fessor Tyndall estimates that an electric dis
charge occurs in one hundred thousandth of
a second, or ten thousand times more rapidly
than nerve transmission. So you see that it
it were possible a man would die by the
process described ten thousand times before
his nerves would have time to communicate
with his brain.
Last winter, for the purpose of ascertain
ing the effect of the electric light current on
the action of the heart, the thorax of a
chloroformed dog caught in Buffalo was
opened, so that the lungs and heart could be
seen in action by forcing respiration as in
conscious life. At the instant when the cur
rent passed through the heart it became a
mass of quivering flesh. It was noticed that
an attempt to breathe was made after the
current was passed through the dog. This
indicated that the brain had not lost its sus
ceptibility to impressions, and shows that in
execution the current should be passed
through the center. It should not be for
gotten, however, that the dog was from
utffalo. The commission couldheaveselected
no tougher subject than a Buffalo dog.
There can be no question, however, that
electricity is the thing to do the business.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84025891/1895-09-07/ed-1/?sp=4&q=Lizzie+Halliday+Lunatic+Asylum+Murder+Electricity</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016758/1899-06-01/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Death+Chair+Penalty+Capital+Punishment+Murder</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Death In the Chair.
The execution of Mrs. Martha M.
Place was a triumph of grisly justice.
To even write about the carrying out
of the death penalty upon a woman is
not a pleasant task, but justice is not
instituted to furnish pleasure. There
are some dire tasks which fall to the
community no less than to the individ
ual that we must contemplate with our
teeth set and our resolution unbent
The law claimed and took its victim in
Bpite of the most energetic and tireless
efforts to save her Every argument
the emotion of pity or horror could
furnish was brought to bear, and a large
part of the community, which is too
busy with its pleasures to waste much
sympathy upon the victims of the mur
deress, found time to appeal in behalf
of the murderess The result is a vindi
cation of the law and afresh respect for
justice, which reassumes a new phasa
of inevitableness and majesty The law
is no respecter of persons, was what the
of New York said when ap
pealed to The well being of the com
munity must be safeguarded, even if
sentiment is outraged, was what he
meant to say On the whole, it is a
healthy return to the rigid defensive
measures which society has established
for its own protection That the ad
vancing temper of civilization is against
capital punishment and that capital
punishment will ultimately be modified
are not at all to the point Whatever
the penalty for murder may be, let it
be inflicted justly and impartially upon
offenders after due conviction, without
regard to other considerations than
those of justice to the innocent</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84028140/1901-10-29/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Repentance+Czolgosz+Electric+Chair+Electrocuted+Deadly+Current</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NO WORD
With Brute Courage Czolgosz Met De
-th
In the Electric Chair.
Cowardice Quivered on His Lips, But Unsustained by Prayer or Hope of Eter
nity He Felt the Mask of Death Upon His Face and Passed to Oblivion,
Hated and Despised.
Auburn, N. Y., Oct 20.-(Spl.)-Loon
F. Czolgosz, alias Fred Nieman, was
successfully electrocuted at Auburn
prison this morning. He was pro
nouncod dead at 7:10:15 a. in.
With the purely animal courage that
bud sustained blm and the Innate cow
ard within him struggling to his lips,
the youthful murderer, hated by tho
nation and tho world at largo, paid the
ponalty for his crime.
Ho took tho chair at 7:15 and In less
itlmo than It takes to tell it, tho deadly
current had paaHod through his body,
rubblnrr 'nmfeshla miserable existence
with merciful and unerring swiftness.
Seated In tho chair, with the fatal
curroilt about to bo applied, Czolgosz,
V facing tho witnesses said;
"I shot the President becauso 1
thought It would benefit good work
ing people by ridding them of abom
inations. I am not sorry for my
crime."
During Oils time tho attendants wcro
busy strapping him to tho enalr. His
last words were: "I am heartily sorry
I did not see my father."
This was said after tho strap had
been drawn across his face, yet his
words were heard distinctly by all tho
witnesses in tho roomi Ho went to
his death unsupported by tho com
forting thought that ho had mado
pence with his God.
For Uie (lrst time In the history of
the prison a condemned man marched
to tlie fatal chair unaccorupnnicd by a
Spiritual advisor, Spiritual aid hod
been offered hUn, but ho scorned all
entreaties. Ho wanted no one to prny
tpt his soiuV
Crolgosz wns awakened from a
sound sleep at tliflO nnd tho death wnr
iant read. He listened without emo
tion and after eating spailngly of
brcnkfa&t, prepared for tho deatll
chain Ho caino In without a tremor,
and took his plnce, saying nothing be
yond tho remarks quoted.
Last evening, Crolgosa reluctantly
recelred Fathers Fudzluskl and
Hlckey. It was late and ho had ouce
refused to meet them. When Uioy
reached tho prleott Supt Collins con
voyed their request for nu Intervlow
to Uie prisoner. Czolgosz Bvjnt back
word that ho did not cwo to seo them,
but tho priests asked to bo allowed to
go to him desplto his rofusal.
Supt Collins consented, and person
ally escorted them to tho cell. I The
priests remained with Czolgosz for
three-quarters of an hour, and earnest
ly pleaded with the prisoner to repeut
and pray for divine forgiveness. He
rejected all their advances, however,
and they regretfully withdrew. They
told the prisoner they would hold
themselves ready to answer a call
from him at any hour of tho night
It was 7 o'clock when Supt Collins
went Into the death house and tried
to get the prisoner to talk to him.
Although he rreinaincd In the cell some
time he was apparently not success
ful In getting anything material from
him.
At 8 o'clock a brother and brother-in-law
arrived, and Supt Collins took
them down to the condemned man's
cell. There was no demonstration
when they met Czolgosz merely
stepped to th0 front of bla stool cage
and said: "Hello." The brother ven
turcd tho remarks: "I wish you would
tell us. Leon, who got you Info this
scrape."
The ossasin answered In a slow, hes
itating manner, "No one; nobody had
anything to do with It but me."
"That Is not how you were brought
up," said the brother, "and you ought
to toll us everything now."
"I haven't got anything to toll," ho
answered In a surly manner.
"Do you want to see tho priests
ngain?" asked his brother, And ho on.
swered with moro vehemenco than ho
had previously shown:
"No, them, don't send them hero
again; I don't want thorn."
Tho brothor-ln-law interjected here:
"That's right, Leon." Tho brother
looked rather disturbed by tho 'answer.
Then stepping up close to the bars,
the condemned man said:
"And don't you have any praying
over ino when I'm dead. I don't want
It I dou't want any of their re
ligion." There was a painful pause of a few
minutes and then the relatives resum
ed casual conversation with him, to
which ho replied In monosyllables, ;m
til the bi other-in-law suggested, much
to Supt. Colllus' emprise, that ho and
the bi other be peimltted to witness
the execution. Before Supt Collins
could reply Leon Czolgosz said:
"Yes, Mr. Superintendent lot them
seo me killed."
Supt. Colllus told tho trio In emphat
ic tonus that no such thing could bo
allowed and oideied them to say good
by. Czolgosz walked to the back of bis
coll, sat down on the edge of his cot
nnd did not answer the last farewell.
When the relatives arrived ut the
warden's office they ugnlii renowed
thou- request to see the execution, to
which Mr. Colons replied: "Emphat
ically no. Czplgosz will be killed at
7 o'clock tomorrow and If you apply
to tho warden in the afternoon you
may bo ablo to seo tho body."
Tho two men were then lot out of the
prison.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1903-10-01/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Chair+Fifteen+Minutes+Van+Wormers+Electrocuted+Willis+Frederick+Burton+Electric</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>3 VAN WORMERS J
J
OlE IN THE CHAIR
IN FifTEEN MINUTES
The Brothers Are Electrocuted One
After the Other with Marvellous
i Speed Without a Hitch in the Triple
Tragedy Each Displaying Nerve
I Willis the Eldest Was the First tcTDie
Then Came Frederick the Youngest
I 1 and Burton Most Composed and De
l termined of All Was the Last
I
I I
QUICK WORK OF DEATH SHOCKS
WILLIS VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
113430 The current was turned into his body one
minute later He was dead at 1137
FRBDBRICK VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
11413O At 1142 the current was turned on He was
declared dead at 114330
I
BURTON VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
1147 The currant wai turned on at 114730 He was
declared dead at 114830
lbe actual time of the triple execution was less than
fifteen minutes
1
Special to The Evening World
DANNEMORA Oct tThe lives of the three Van Wormer boys
p tyho were condemned to death for the murder of Peter Hallenbeck were
forfeited to the tw In extraordinarily quick time today The ceremony
1 of shocking them to death in the elecfrtfc chair consumed but thirty sec
I onds over fifteen minutes That length of time elapsed from the moment
when y1illis Van Wormer left his cell and started for the death chamber
until the physicians pronounced Burton Van Wormer the last of the trio
deadTherewas
Therewas not a hitch in the proaling The fascinated witnesse
sat and watchedandvscarcely breathed as ihe men were led in killed anc
carried out with strict adherence to a prearranged time table The boy
died with the most surprising composure None can tell the horrible
ordeal through which Burton Van Wormer passed as he awaited his turn
3Ut he showec no sign of fear when led out to face his doom
GLOOM TO BEFIT TIlE OCCASION
It was an eternity of gloom within the purlieus ot Clinton walls am
black ae an Ink well upside down
t At 1135 oclock five minutes earlier than usual the prison whistle
ii which regulates the life of tho penitentiary and marks the uprisings an
downslttlngs of tho people in the village of Dannemora gave fortlh a
shrieking blast The whirring wheels and belts in tho factories came to c
rest and the time of tho triple killing had arrived A boll rang In the
Wardens office and a guard appeared at tho door and beckoned to the wit
nesses Two by two they followed him to the rear of the administration
I building through the alleyway which Is between the north tter of con
demned cells and the structure wall
r As they passed a mumble Of voices came from the quarters of the
doomed Father Beranger who hail been so attentive to the condemned
f men was with the Van Wjornjors giving promises of hope and receiving
responses of belief
Tho ears ot theboys must have heard the tread of many feet going
by The death watchers said after the legal tragedy had ended that they
i heard and that their limbs shook
Soon tho crowd was in the chamber of death and each ones seat was
pointed out to him as ln a playhouee and each sat down to talk In
whispers with his neighbors With their eyes upon the stage and its grue
some 5ettgatbe chair with leathern straps and strange metal fittings
they had not long to wait before the curtain was rung up
The breaths of the witnesses could be heard at times as they sat there
and waited The noise of the opening of a lock made a rasping sound be
t hind the scenes and a catch came Into cacti ones throat There was the
f round of shuffling feet on the cement floor outside the door of death Now
L 1t was afthe threshold now Inside Some turned their heads to look most
4 stared straight ahead at the chair
WILLIS LED TO HIS DOOM
The priest with book In hand and murmuring llpg walked ahead Be
hind them came two strong guards and between them was Willis Van
Wormer He showed not a sign of fear
s Three paces brought the grim procession in front of the chair Other
ff guards were there ready to fasten the straps and the murderer fell into the
tt 1 jeai The States executioner lowered the electrode the hood with wet
brl sponges on it which makes the shock of the deadly current sure and the
1 mask dropped The hands that did these things worked quickly surely as
a w mane knitting They felt ona of the ma a legs where a little wire
with a wet sponge at the end of it was fixed They pressed it closer to tho
limb and then went over to a cabinet
There wna a vicious snakelike sound as if one should ejaculate some
thing that when spelled Bounded like Ss6spit
i The witnessed started Some of thorn heaved and shuddered like tho
form in the chair The death switch had been turned o t The room was as
a tomb In the middle pf a lovely night</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024827/1912-08-11/ed-1/?sp=12&q=Victims+Death+Chair+Execution+Electric+Executed+Electricity</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Twenty-two
jears ago this week, on August C,
1890, William Kemmlcr, a condemned
murderer, was put to death In the
electric chair In Auburn prison. Kern.
mler ttas the first victim to be legal
ly executed by electricity in tb Unit
ed States and his case was the sub
ject of wide discussion at the time.
The action of New York In substitut
ing the electric chair for the gallows
has been found generally satisfact
ory and her example has been fol
lowed by Ohio, Virginia, South Caro
lina, Massachusetts, Kentucky auJ
New Jersey.
ijlnce the execution of Kemmler
there hae been 151 persona put to
death In the electric chair In New
York. The state prison authorities
estimate that It costs about J4000 per
individual to carry, out the capital
punishment mandate. On the basis
of Oils estimate New York state haa
expended about JC3.000 for electro
cutions since that form of Inflicting
the death penalty was introduced.
Several times the electric chair at
Sing Sing has had two victims in
one day, and on one occasion a short
time ago three persons were put to
death within a period of twenty-four
hours. Rut never before has there
been such a wholesale execution of
death sentences Imposed on prison
ers In this state as is scheduled to
take place at Sing Sing next week.
Nino men are to die on the same
day, and In as rapid succession H3
they can be led to the death chair.
-:ix of the nine prospective victims
are the Italians who were convicted
of the atrocious murder of Mrs Mary
Hall at Croton Id Kit. Westchester
County, on Nov 9, 1911.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86061215/1915-07-31/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Death+Electric+Chair+Electrocuted+Executed+Execution+Murdered+Rosenthal</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Electric Chair Gets Men Who Murdered Rosenthal
£L&C7WC
CHA/&
S/A/G vT/Att
ik
Lsrry lows
which I must die. You are now about
to witness my destruction by the state,
which is organized to protect the lives
of the innocent! May'Almighty God
pardon everyone who has contributed
In any degree to my untimely death.
And now on the brink of my grave I
declare to the world that I am proud
to have been the husband of the pur
est, noblest woman that ever lived—
Helen Becker. This acknowledgment
is the only legacy I can leave her. I
bid you all good-bye. Father, 1 am
ready to go. Amen/'
(Signed) "Charles Becker."
Talks All Night.
After his wife had said farewell,
shortly after midnight, Becker main
tained a casual conversation with
Deputy Warden Johnson who sat be
side tne screen in front of his cell.
Sometimes he smoked cigars, after
jwhich he would let his head fall on
I his hand and gaze reflectively at the
I floor for minutes at a time. Dawn
found him seated on the edge of his
cot carefully pinning a photograph of
his wife on his white shirt just over
his heart. Then, as if he desired to
have her all to himself, Becker put on
a thin black alpaca coat, which he
tightly buttoned. The photograph was
not seen by the witnesses until the
prison" physician opened his coat as he
sat in the death chair.
Becker was put to death by the state
executioner whose name is unknown
to the public. This man succeeded
State Electrician Davis and he said he
would not take the job unless his name
wis kept secret. He lives in a little
town up-state and went about his
work briskly.
Becker's executioner said that in his
opinion the man had died instantly at
the first contact.
Negro Follows Becker.
An autopsy on the body of Becker
was performed, according to law, im
mediately after the execution. After
Becker's body had been removed from
the electric chair, Samuel Haynes, a
nefgro murderer, was brought into the
execution room and electrocuted. One
of Becker's last requests to Warden
Osborne was that''he be put to death
before Haynes.
Mrs. Becker Makes Statement.
A statement credited to Mrs. Becker
was given out here shortly after her
husband's death.
"I shall never rest," she was quoted
as aaying, "until I have exposed the
metl ods which were used to convict
my husband. Whether he was guilty
or innocent, there was no justification
for the means employed to convict
him.
"I would rather lose all the other
members of my family, as dear as they
are to me, than lose Charlie. No one
can take his place. In all of the ten
years of our married life I never had
occasion once to regret that I was his
wife</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045389/1916-03-05/ed-1/?sp=48&q=Die+Death+Electric+Chair+Electrocution+Electricity</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Scientists Have Just Discovered
Many Secrets Which Have Long
Puzzled Them in Regard to Death
by Electric Shock From the Exper
ience of a Man Who Was Electro
cuted and Brought
Back to Life
WHKN the electric chair was sub
stituted for the old fashioned
gallows in New York it was be
cause it was believed that electrocution
was painless. But just what were the
sensations of death in the electric chair
scientists were unable to say, because
no electrocuted victim came back to life
to tell tliern.
It was assumed that the shock of the
powerful current would instantly render
the condemned man unconscious. But
the unpleasant feature of m^st electro
cutions has been the necessity of re
penting the shock several times. This
was not foreseen
Experience in ilie death chamber has
shown that the electric current does
not usually destroy life at the tirst shock.
Evidences of pulsating life compel the
executioner to turn on the current asain
and yet again. This distressing failure
of the electric charge to instantly end
life has caused much speculation among
scientists and humanitarians.
Does the first shock end the conscious
ness of the condemned man?
Or is the victim siiil conscious?hover
ing between death and life, does themau
In the chair realize what is going on?
What, if any, was the agony of the
ti rs shock?
What were the agonies of the victim
during the moments elapsing between
tiie tirst shock and the second impact of
the current? Was he entirely uncon
scious, partly conscious or fully conscious
of the horrors of the situation which the
law never meant to be inflicted on him?
And if the tirst shock of the current
benumbed the condemned man's brain,
did returning consciousness bring with it
tortures of bodily misery which have
never been known or suspected?
The Victim
Falls Apparently Dead.
Nobody has been able to answer these
questions until an accident happened
viiit-h unexpectedly illuminated this wholo
subject of what the victim in the elec
tric chair really sees, hears, foels and
cu ffers.
It was the morning of February 3 that
Harry Ton sous pushed his hand truck
of steel castings into th^ freight elevator
of the National Screw and Tack Com
pany. in Cleveland. His left foot stepped
firmly on a "live" wire, which had ac
cidentally become detae.hed from the elec
tric controller of the elevator. Tonious'
face paled. He dropped the truck, ut
tered a heartrending cry, and fell lifeless
to the floor.
The ambulance surgeon, who soon ar
rived with two police attendants, declared
that Tonious was dead and that it was
a Coroner's case. Hut hoping that some
thing might be done to resuscitate the
man, the surgeon ordered the body to be
brought to the hospital for experiments
with the pulrnotor.
After vigorous work the left leg of
Tonious was seen 14V(remhie slightly. On?
of the physician^ h?ahed over and put
his ear to the man's breast. There was
a slight flutter heard.
The pulmotor was applied more vigor
ously than ever. Other measures for re
suscitation were taken and before long
the "dead" man's body stirred and his
lips moved. The next moment his eye
lids fluttered and lie shook his shoulderp,
as if throwing off a heavy load. Sub
consciously his left hand moved in the
direction of the left foot?the member
which had come in contact with the wire.
One of the doctors opened one of the
kirn's eyes and saw the eyeball roll to
one side, and then back again. Life was
beginning to assert Itself, and a moment
later Tonious tried to rise, but was held
fast by toe attendants, delighted that the
object of their attention had been brought
back to life.
Life returned by leaps and bounds and
the "dead" man was soon able to open
his eyes ami talk. Two days later Tonious
was allowed to stand and walk a f"\v
steps. His whole bodj was still weak
and he was extremely nervous. His feet
could scarcely bear the weigh; of his
frame.
He regained his strength quickly, and
TJ tw o mor?- da -s ;ts tal.en t.o !:is home.
The doctors i< ::li/.f,d tin: in the person
of the uiifo: Tonious they had a
man who lia l virtually been through all
the experiences >>r an eloctrocuted vic
tim?with ilie very import air addition
that Tonious had coin" back to life and
full consc.ensue* and wa? abb to nippiy
the answers to t ie mysteries which liav
heretofore always been burled with the
remains of the electrocuted murderers
Pressed 'or information on all the as
pects of i- markab'.e experience,
Tonious said:
"Dying wa- quick and without much
pain. Coming ba< to life was slow and
very painful.
"When 1 stared to hacK out of the
elevator." Toniou continued, I recall
stepping "ti the wire. I could feel it
under my fe>ot. Then felt a teirible
jolt on thf- back of my head It felt as
if some one had struck me there with a
club. 1 remember having cried out, but
my voice seemed to trail off in tin* nis
taace. It felt as if a bomb bad been
inserted in rny skull and as if it bad
exploded and blown off the top of my
head.
"Then it aeemed as if a million needles
nnd pins were shooting through my body.
They pricked all at the same time. The
top of my head seemed to rise. 1 felt
the ground giving way under my feet as
?if I were on the brink of a precipice the
edge of which had crumbled under me.
I felt myself falling. There was nothing
to support me. 1 realized that no part of
mv body was moving of its own accord,
but the whole of me kept falling. All this
appeared to be in a short space of titer,
probably no more than a few seconds,
ami then finally l felt as if i were float
ing in space. 1 couldn't see. hear, smell
or feel anything, and then suddenly oil
was a blank. I just couldn't think or re
member anything.
"I remember now that, when I stepped
oil the wire 1 felt no sensation in my leg
ft'r foot. It was al! in my he'.l. At the
time, after realizing I had stepped on a
wire, I forgot all about my leg nnd foot.
Only my head was in pain, "fliera was
no mark or burn on either my shoe, my
sock, or my foot. The pain of the jolt
and the explosion in my head and of the
needles and pins through my body was
intense.
"After my mind had been a blank. 1
don't know how long, as I had no idea
of tim? or anything else, I began to hear.
.My first realization was of the sound of
rushing water or a heavy wind. Il sound
ed like when you stand on ihe beach at
'lie lake when the waves are lil^h -a
sort of roaring sound. I heard the roar
ing first, and what seemed then like a few
minutes later the sound increased and 1
could hear a kind of whistle, like the wind
makes. When I first began to hear it
seemed as if I had been holding my ears
shut, keeping out all the sound, arid then
gradually releasing the pressure, the
sound growing louder and louder.
"While 1 didn't realize I was coming
b-iek to life. I did think that whatever
had happened I had been hearing the
noise for a lonrr time. It seemed hours.
I didn't realize wlm! was going on, my
only impression being that I was hearing
something.
"As the. sounds grew louder, as if
bigger waves were dashing on the beach
and the force of the wind had increased,
The Secret
Chamber in
Which Is Hidden
the Electrician,
Who Is the Keai
Executioner
sRflu
The Condemned Man
they started to swish back and forth.
'I hat is, it seemed to me as if the sounds
moved, if that were possible. They would
grow dim and I thought they were going
away from me. and then they would come
nearer. I didn't consider whether I could
nee or not. and didn't wonder why could
not use any other sens" than hearing.
1 didn't wonder where 1 was or what had
happened to me. I just kept thinking of
those sounds.
"What seemed to m<> ages later ihe
sounds began to grow louder and louder,
Why Docto</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030431/1919-08-03/ed-1/?sp=27&q=Deans+Death+Sing+Sings+Tragic+Hour+Electric+Chair+Electricity+Electrocuted+Capital+Punishment</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>Deans of the Death Watch Tell
WALL DhHIND WH CH CONDEMNED Msfei NStfT rrarV -t u vasl l vpgf "WMBMff&M
Weird and Thrill
ing Incidents That
Marked Last Days
of Many Famous
Murderers Are Re
called by Three
of the Prison's
Veteran Guards
Br EDWARD T. KAVANAUGH.
T"T TEIRD arid thrilling have been
A some of the experiences of
George Meserole and two
other veteran Blag Bine keepers, lately'
retired, with numerous murderers, fa-
mous or Infamous, during many years
they were on the death watch over
the prison's efclls set apart for pris
oners awaiting execution,
Meserole, whoso keen eyes for twenty-six
years kept a lookout over thoso
closely guarded cells. Is only now un-
folding some Interesting stories of
what has gone on In there. John Der-
renbachcr, who kept vigil over the
death cells nine years, and Alexander
Van Wart, who did relief duty there
for a similar period, have likewise
elected to talk. With official consent
rof Warden Edward V. Brophy they
feel at liberty to give their reminis
cences. Many -of the epldaaes de
scribed have never before been writ'
ten.
Meserole'a Fumona Charges.
Meserole had by far the longest
deathhouie experience and came In
contact with its most celebrated In
mates, such as Albert T.Patrick ac
cused of the murder of William Rice,
the millionaire, whose 6cntenco was
finally commuted: Roland Mollneux,
first convicted and later" acquitted oi
the murder of Mrs. Katherlne Adams:
D- Samuel Kennedy, charged with the
murder of Dolly Reynolds, who was
afterward retried and discharged, and
m ntiita -n,VAt nAl1rA 1lutfnnn. who
was convicted for the murder of Ro
senthal, the gambler. These and other
distinguished prisoners were entrusted
to Meserole' keeping. Two hundred
condemned persons, including three
women, have been received In his time.
Standing between a condemned mur
derer facing death in the electric
chair and his freedom, the watchman's
task in the condemned cells Is a tick
lish one. A murJerer condemned to
die has nothing to lose by Killing a
guard to make a getaway. The temp
tation to attack his guard Is, therefore.
obvious. Yet none of these three
keepers ever received even a scratch,
nor' had a suicide or scape on his tour
of duty. Tet they have guarded scores
of dangerous murderers. Other guards
have hrid murder, suicide and escapes
on their shifts.
Comedy and Tragedy.
Both comedy 'and tragedy figure In
r these three veterans' adventures. For
example. Meserole well remembers tno
"day in 1916 that Hyman Ltebman,
who threw his two children out of a
window and killed them in New York,
shammed suicide, He pretended, in
staging an insanity plea, to have swal
lowed poison, when ur, Amos u.
Saulre got to work on him with the
dreaded stomach pump, it soon arew
tho truth, as well as the harmless vin
egar he swallowed, out of him. Lleb
man shrieked and begged for mercy
as the doctors pumped away, and had
to confess he was faking so they
would stop the pump. Then, on the
pathetic side, there was the proceo
slon of seven hearses up to the prison
front door on the eve of the execution
of Vincent Colli and six other slayers
In Warden Kennedy's time. This was
the largest number ever executed In
one batch.
In Intellect Meserole, Derrenbacher
and Van Wart are ahove the average
prison guard. There was never any
thing surly or shiftless about them.
Bach is polished and unassuming.
But all three In their deathhouse
duties were firm and fearless. They
were able to match their wits and
their daring against thoso of their
chargos, whether they be murderer
of the shrewd typo or more brutes.
Meserole had fearlessness Instilled in
him In the civil war. For bravery in
the Union army he roso fromthe
ranks to lieutenant in Duryea's Zou
aves regiment.
In point of deathhouso experience
Derrenbacher is the dean of the group.
He went to work In Sing Sing June
U0, 1889, Under Warden Brush and lad
been there but a month when on July
18, 1889, the dynamo and nil the elec-
GEORGE MESER.OLE. WHO GUARDED SING
SING'S DEWU-HOUSE TWENTY SIX VEAfiU
trie apparatus for the first electric
execution arrived at the prison.
New Tork State had just passed a
law substituting the electric chair for
the hangman's noose. There had
never been an electric execution and
everybody was prospecting as to who
would be the first person electrocuted
and'whether he would bo killed with
out conscious suffering or tortured to
death. f
On October 30, 1889, Warden Brush
received Charles McElvalne, aged
twenty, the first person sentenced to
the electric-' chair., He had- slain
Christian Lucca In Brooklyn. There
had been no deathhouse built then.
So"McElvalne was placed' in a cell on
the upper floor of tho hospital building
end kepA In 'solitary conflneme'nt;-' On
December 5, 1889, work of building tho
deathhouse was begun. It was to be,
virtually, a prison within a prison.
Derrenbachcr saw Thomas Palllster,
a prisoner, helping to build it. By
an odd turn of events, this same pris
oner was later convicted of murder
and lodged, two years later, in the
prison death cells himself. He was
never executed. He cheated the chair
by escaping,
Deathhouse Snon Crowded.
Soon as the deathhouse was finished
McKlvalne became Its first occupant.
Derrenbacher was his first guard
there. Ho would keep watch over the
condemned murderer eleven hours a
day. McElvalne hud not the exclusive
use of' the deathhouse long. On New
Year's day Sheheok Julglgo, a Japa
nese, was received from Manhattan
for killing Seaman Coutaln, a Japanese
sailor.
Then came Joseph Woodwho killed
Charles Ruflln, a laborer on the new
Croton aqueduct at Klngsbrldge, fol
lowed a few weeks later by Harris
Smller, who shot Mary Dralney, one ot
his three bigamous wives, and then by
James J. Blocum, a baseball player,
whtf beat his wife to death.
There was room for only four In the
original deathhouse, so Smller was
placed in the hospital loft. Keeper
Fagan, on watch there, fell asleep one
night while on duty. Principal Keeper
James Connaughton, a rigorous dis
ciplinarian, discovered him In the midst
of his nap. He rebuked and suspended
Fagan immediately. Next came Nicola
Trcrzq, the murderer who was aiter
ward saved by Gov. Flower, who com
muted his sentence to life imprison
ment. An addition was built to the death-
house so It could accommodate eight
men. On his -shift Derrenbacher alone
in the deathhouse watched six mur
derers. As they were cramped badly
In the, brick cells, Moserole was as
signed by Connnughtop.ln 1891 to take
each murderer out hls cage a half
hour a day for exercise. McElvalne,
of a nervous nature, often bored
Meserole and the other keepers by
scratching his cell bars In filing his
finger nails or using his bunk sheot to
swat flies with.
Horse Used to Test Chair
As tho time drew near for tho first
execution, Warden Brush wished to
test the killing capacity of the new
contrivance. So on Nov. 20, 1890, a
horse was taken from the prison stable
and fastened to the death chair In a
room adjoining tho condemned colls,
where Derrenbacher was on duty. The
keepers fastened a hood, over the
horse's head, as they do now over tho
cranium of a murderer, and tied the
steed fast to the chair.
As the current was turned on a fuse
blew out and the horso got only a part
of the shock that was meant for It. It
made a weird shrieking noise and
kicked the wall furiously.
The commotion Btartled Slocum.
"What's that?" asked the wife slayer.
Derrenbacher knew they were testing
the chair, but would not add to
Slocum's mental torture. "It s only a
horse kicking," replied the keeper,
Little did Slocum realize they were
trying out tho chair to use on the
deathhouse Inmates. Or that destiny
intended that he should be the first
person ever to sit in it
Derrenbacher had the most trying
Si
1,
ordeal of his long prison career oil July
7, 1891, the day of the first executions.
The whole prison was astir and all the
murderers In the deathhouse were in
a frenzy. Outside a morbid mob lined
the hills overlooking tho prison and
the streets looking to it
Warden Brown had pledged all who
would have access to the condemned
cells and the death chamber to se
crecy. Newspaper reporters were not
only forbidden to see the execution
(they hod been allowed to witness
hangings) but the warden put out
armed sentries and kept them off the
prison property entirely. He had a
cordon ot guards form a "dead line."
Sentries paced back and forth with
rifles to overawe tho crowd and shoot
anybody who might attempt to -.slip
through tno line. Tno warden, ior
going to such pains, was JJorover after
ward called 'Deadline" Brown.
However, Brown arranged a code of
signals to let reporters and others
know when each of the four prisoners
to be electrocuted was dead. He se
lected a white (lag for Sloqum, a blue
flag for Smller, a black flag for Wood
and a red flag for Julglgo. When each
man was dead his flag was to go up
the halyards on the root of the war
den's residence. So the thousands
awaiting outside the prison -riveted
their gaze on the flagpole.
Derrenbacher was told to get Slocum
ready first. He bid the unfortu
nate feilow good-by nnd about noon
Slocum was taken on the death march
to the execution chamber a few yards
away. State Detective -James Jack
son and Keeper Sylvester McNeal
quickly strapped him in the chair. The
electrodes were jammed down on his
head, the mask drawn over his face,
and Dr. Carlos Macdonald, the alienist,
signalled the executioner to pull the
switch. Tho current shot on, Slocum
lunged forward and tugged at the
straps. Tho first shock had left him
unconscious, but another was given
him to make death certatn. Slowly
went the white flag up tho halyards
Quaint Recollections of Drink and
By HAROLD SETON.
HAKESPEARE has intimated that
the province ot the stage is to
"hold the mirror up to Nature."
Therefore his plays, first published by
two actors of his company, are sup
posed to reflect the manners of his
time. Coming down through the plays
of Congreve, Wycherley and Far-
quanar, Hlcnard urinsiey Hlierman, to.
the plays of Sydney Grundy, Arthur
Wing Plnero and Henry Arthur Jones,
all ot theso authors refer to drink and
drinkers, either in a comic or a tragic
manner, to point or adorn a talc. But
now that prohibition has come upon
us and hard stuff is no longer expected
to exist, scenes of Intoxication on the
stage will presumably be taboo.
This leads us to recall various In
stances In which thesplans havo been
called upon to simulate Inebriety, and
some of these recollections are quaint
and curious. For instance, It may sur
prise and shock the present generation,
which only knows Maude Adams as
Cinderella and Peter Pan, perhaps even
as the heroine of "What Every Woman
Knows," "Quality Street." and "The
Little Minister," to. learn that one of
her first big hits was made In 1892 In
"The Masked Ball," in which, as lead
ing lady to John Drew, she was repre
sented as haying imbibed too freely I
May Robson, who In a long and va
ried career has played all sorts of
parts tn all sorts ot plays, met with
considerable success several seasons
ago when she starred In "The Rejuve
nation of Aunt Mary," in which she
was supposed to be a respectable old
lady who takes a new lease on life nnd
consorts with individuals many years
her junior. In one scene, surrounded
by several lively youths, she becomes
grotesquely hilarious.
Blanche Walsh Inclined rather to
tragic ports than'to comic ones, and In
two of her best known starring ven
tures, "Resurrection," by Count Leo
Tofetoy, and "The Woman "In ?flie
'ilinf r'l iirhliflllilHi (.lAfrlf 'if -''.EfrH V-
THE SUN, SUNDAY,
HIIBHBBIklllsBSslI
gCtL. ALEXANDER VAN WART.
SriMKbUhr- UFHCEK IN
outside. .The mob .realized the new
experimental' electric device had done
its grejsome work and that Slocum
was tho first to go.
Derrenbacher then got Smller ready,
bid him good-by and saw htm led oil
to the deadly contrivance Next he
opened the cell door for Wood, shook
his hand and bid him good-by. Final
ly Derrenbacher unlocked the cell of
Julglgo. Because tho Japanese was a
powerful and brutal man tho prison
authorities feared trouble from him.
So they left him until tho last. Julglgo,
however, surprised them. He nodded
good-by to 'Derrenbacher, walked erect
to the chair and went to his death as
stolid as an ox.
Derrenbacher remembers how brave
ly McElvalne faced the chair. "He
walked upright and quickly," said the
keeper, "sat squarely down in the chair
and said: 'Let'er got
Tho prison deathhouso was shy two
murderers when Derrenbacher report
ed for work the morning of April 21,
1893. During the night Palllster and
Case," by Clyde Fitch, she had thrill-'
lng scenes of intoxication.
In another Russian play, "Redemp
tion," produced last season, John Bar
rymore gave a vivid portrayal of de
bauchery and drunkenness, thereby
gaining recognition as one of the fore
most actors of the day. By a curious
coincidence. In "The Jest," which fol
lowed "Redemption," Lionel Barry
more had a drunken scene and he
proved himself quite as expert a de
lineator of dipsomania as brother
John, with whom he shared stellar
honors.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1926-08-07/ed-1/?sp=20&q=electric+chair+criminals</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>Paint Criminals’ Faces Blue
Or Tatto Them. That Would Discourage Crime.
A dozen New York criminals, called the “Oberst Gang,”
whined, wept and begged for the pity of witnesses that will
probably send some of them to the electric chair. Mr. Herbert
Swope causes one of his editorial minions to suggest that
ONLY the electric chair frightens such criminals; therefore,
the electric chair should be preserved.
But torture on the rack, or boiling alive in oil, would
frighten them MORE than the electric chair, and that is no
reason why civilization should disgrace itself either with the
rack or the electric chair. The question is “What should
civilized men do?” not “What do criminals fear?”
Criminals fear hard work even more than they fear the
electrio chair. If they knew .that conviction would mean hard
work for life, many would reform, and they fear permanent
IDENTIFICATION.
If there is a distinct criminal class, why not IDENTIFY it
PERMANENTLY, by staining the faces of all convicted high
waymen, holdup men, etc., a dark blue, by tatooing or some
other process that would make the stain permanent. Cocaine
could make it painless. Many of the rising young criminals
would dislike spending the rest of their lives with a blue face,
a permanent mark of past conviction. And what a useful
warning that “blue face” would be to honest men!
The Pardon Board might let them out of prison, but it
couldn’t take away that mark that would warn the public.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/2022239691/1924-08-06/ed-1/?sp=1&q=electric+chair+criminals</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>STATE PORT TERMINAL MEASURE IS PASSED BY GEORGIA SENATE
Seénate Votes Electric
Chair for Criminals
MEASURE, MUST PASS HOUSE
'AND GOVERNOR AND THEN
GO TO PEOPLE
ATLANTA, Aug. 6.—The port
terminal bill providing for submis
sion to the people a constitutional
amendment under which fifteen mil
‘lion in bonds would be issued,
passed the seate today.
Wimberly Bill Recommitted
ATLANTA, Aug. 6.—The resolu
tion of Representative Wimberly, of
Toombs, to investigate the Georgia
Public Service Commission, was fav
orably reported eoday by the judi
ciary committee.
It was ordered recommitted to the
game committee on motion of Sena
tor Johns. Johns stated the commit
tee meeting was not so fully attend
ed as desired.
message that the biennial sessions
sjll had passed.
‘Substitute Electric Chair
ATLANTA, Aug. 6.—by a 26 to
‘2l vote the senate today passed the
Phillips bill providing for, substitu
‘tion of the electric chair for hang
ing as a legal method of execution
for convicted criminals in Georgia.
Consolidation City and County
S\’QLANTA, Aug. 6.—The house
"O%ay began the consideration of the
Bilr"ﬁi‘iigﬁlg consolidation of city
and county governments in Jities.
excepting Atlanta which have a pop
-ulatio in excess of 31,000.
Consideration of the consolidation
proposal came after the house voted
to take the Lankford income tax
bill from the table to the calendar..
The bill was tabled last year by the
“house,
ONE MISSING, TWO HURT
LAKEVIEW, 0., Aug. 6.—Chas.
Treadmore, of Russells Point, is
missing and two are in hospitals,
one of them seriously burned, as the
result of an explosion and fire
wrecking a steam launch today on
Indian Lake.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86079068/1913-05-20/ed-1/?sp=1&q=electric+chair+criminals</id>
<rel>0</rel>
<text></text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1940-12-22/ed-1/?sp=69&q=electric+chair+criminals</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>Meet the Murderer
By Warden Lewis E. Lawes. New York: Harper Bros.
The huge iron gates of Sing Sing Prison swing open every day to
admit prisoners of all types and classes, and meeting them all for the last
20 years has been Warden Lewis E, Lawes. During his tenure as chief of
the famous New York penal institution he has compiled many case his
tories dealing with murderers whose lives and personalities he has been
a position to study first-hand.
Warden Lawes is not new to the writing profession, having written
other books, among them “Twenty Thousand Years in Sing Sing and
“Invisible Stripes.” In "Mfcet the Murderer.’ his latest venture^ he has
riven the public the benefit of these case histories, combined with colorful
and intimate observations of life within the penitentiary walls.
This book introduces murderers whose crimes have made front-page
^An. as well as obscure criminals who have gone quietly and without
Snfare to death in the electric chair. There are criminals who made a
profession of murder, as well as those who killed m a fit of passion. The
men who spend their last days on “Death Row have left behind a trail
erf sordid crime. The book, however, is not sordid. Each case history, none
hi so much detail as to be boring, is presented to the reader in a smooth
flowing, entertaining style, introducing here and there an occasional touch
Sing Sing makes a deep impression on those unfortunates whose lives
are spent behind its somber walls, but it is strangely true that some
murderers also make a lasting impression on Sing Sing. Contrary to all
belief, murderers cause less trouble in prison than any other type of
Lawes has exploded many age-old theories, among them the
over.worked expression. “The condemned man ate a hearty breakfast
“Sometimes, the dishes on a prisoner’s last tray would give a person
with a cast-iron stomach indigestion just to look at the weird combination
of food,” the warden writes. One might wonder how a condemned man
*ould down such a conglomeration of food and live to reach the electric
chair. The answer is that he eats practically nothing. He hasn’t the
appetite to eat.”
Several interesting facts have been set forth in this book, among them
the fact that whenever the newspapers announce the date of an execution,
at least five people write offering to go to the chair in place of the doomed
man- that hundreds of letters are received from people who want to
become public executioner, and that 20 per cent of the applicants are
women and that 70 per cent of all Sing Sing murderers in the last 20 years
had never been in conflict with the law prior to the crime for which they
paid with their lives. ROBERT A. ERWIN.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88064469/1909-03-23/ed-1/?sp=2&q=electric+chair+criminals</id>
<rel>0</rel>
<text></text>
</result>
</results>
</topic>




<topic>
<id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-siamese-twins</id>
<results>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86053954/1844-11-21/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>The Siaasiiese Twins.
We extract from the letter of a correspondent
of the South Carolina Spartan" the following
account of Chang and Eng, and their families
''You maybe aware that some few years
since, the Siamese Twins, Chang and Eng,
retired from the public jjaze, and settled down
in this county (Wilkes) as farmers. You will
also recollect, that during last year it was pub
lished in some of the newspapers that they had
married two sisters. This notice was treated
as a hoax by some of the journals, and 1 in
cline to think that public opihion settled that
the twins were still living in single blessedness.
To my surprise I find that the supposed hoax
is a literal fact and that these dislinguished
characters are married men Mrs. C. and Mrs.
E. are well known to several of my personal
acquaintances, and are said to be very amiable
and industrious. Each of the ladies has pre
sented her particular a lord" with an heir, in the
person ofa fine, fat, bouncing daughter!
It is said that Chang and Eng, with their
wives and children, contemplate making a tour
through this country in a year or two. The
twins enjoy excellent health are very lively,
talkative, and apparently happy and will doubt
less prove more interesting and attractive in
their second tour than they did in their first
over the civilized world. Having families to
provide fdr, as prudeht husbands and fathers,
they may think their bachelor fortune is insuf
ficient for all the little Changs and Engs of
which they. now have the promise.'</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042204/1848-07-08/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>The Siamese Twins. These attached
brothers, who have been residing on a
farm in North Carolina for about nine
years, intend to leave home on a profes
sional tour through the Southern and Wes
tern States. They have a thriving planta
tion and exhibit among other fruits of
their husbandry three children each. Mrs.
Chang and Mrs. Eng are sisters. They
were both" married at the same time, and
their children pair off admirably as regards
age. Between the first and' second chil
dren in the two families, the difference of
age is only eight or nine days.
When asked how they like workingon
the farm, the twins generally reply, "we
like him much; him very good business
for us." They do not express any desire
to revisit Siam, being, as they say, "Ame
ricans now, and wives and children, they
Americans too."</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042147/1850-10-02/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>THE pAMESE TWINS AT HOME.
The recent contradictory reports in regard to the
death of the Siamese twins, have recalled to our re
collection an account of a visit paid them some two
years since, by a gentleman who made notes of what
he saw and heard at the time the substance of which
we proceed to give to our readers.
After being exhibited in England and this country
for some years, and becoming tired of a migatory
lite, they settled down, strangely enough, in the
mountains of North Carolina, where they were
both married that is to say-each took a wife. These
were two sisters, named Adelaide and Sarah Lates
who were both quite youthful (under twenty years
of age,) when they entered into this strange union, j
They were married at the same time. So far as the j
young women were concerneo, u seems mat an went
smoothly enough during the court-ship but the two
brothers differed as to which should have Sarah, the
largest of the girls, and who is now a bouncing wo
man of some two hundred pounds, avoirdupois. Both
perferred the same individual, in the true spirit of.
tkoir nMMiliar Iwinahin Rnor hnwever. nrevailed I
.7
and the more ponly tairone became nis wnne v.nang
had to content himself with Adelaide who, by the j
way, to any but an oriental taste, was much the pret-
tiest being, in fact a very handsome and showy bru-
ne
Chang and Eng first established themselves, built
a house, and opened a small country shop, or store, on
rrapp-Hill, in V ilkes county, North Carolina. A
Mr. Hams, who had travelled with them while they
were exhibited in the United States, at first assisted I
them in their new business; but in consequence of i
his not marrying to the taste of Mrs. Chang and Mrs. j
limg tne twins aismissea mm, ana since mat time
have managed for themselves. The opinion of Eng
is always the law and Chang cheerfully submits, as
in the case ot selecting their wives, xatg signs ail seemed to think it would be a terrible fate. But his
the witings required in the course ot their business reasonf and experience loo, we mav suppose, told
makes all the bargains, and throughout all their af- j him that Ulis tnreat would never be carried into exe
fairs, appears to be the controlling spirit. It is said, cut-,on fje tried however for a little while to amuse
however (at least Mrs. Eng says,) that her husband j himsef with his mother's gloves, but they were
has much the best disposition ot the two; is much j
kinder to their slaves, (ol which they have a number,
than Chang. They can handle an axe with much j
tiirff? and dexteritv nlaeincr their four hands, and i
j i o
exerting their united strength upon the implement at
the same time. They shoot their game, (being tond
of hunting,) with all the hands of both resting upon
the gun, sometimes one directing tne aim, ana some-
times me omer. in waiKing, or sianuiug, hm near-
est arm of each usually reaches around the waist, or
lies across the other s shoulder.
About the time they settled themselves in North
Carolina, they applied under a law of the State, and
had the name of Bunker added to their Christian, or,
(as I should have said,) Siamese appellates. This
was deemed necessary to a more legal, or formal trans
action of their business, in regard to real estate. Mr.
Bunker is their agent in New York and is under
stood to have some $10,000 invested for the twins
the annual interest of which is employed by them
in their North Carolina operations. I hey scrupu-
lously forbear to touch the principal sum lu Mr. Bun-
ker's hands. Since their location on Trap-Hill, they j
have purchased another plantation in Surry some j
forty miles distant; and at the time our informant
visited them Chang and Eng were residing there, j
while Sarah, Eng's wife, and her children were at:
the Trap-Hill establishment. As in point of time, j
the first call was upon her she, at first, is here en- i
titled to notice.
He found her with three children two girls and a
boy; the latter of whom is called Decatur. Their
flat, swarthy features, black coarse hair, and low, re
treating forehead, indicated clearly their Siamese pa
ternity. In the large room where the guests were
received, stood an enortnons bed, some ten feet in
width which Mrs. Lng Bunker explained, with all i
the innocence and naivette imaginable, was brought i
into requisition whenever her husband, his brother
and her sister visited Trap-Hill. 44 Nothin shorter," j
she said, 44 would do for them all. The woman,
herself, was good looking, though rather corpulent;
with rich auburn hair, fine teeth, and hazel eyes. The
house was neatly kept; the supper spread for the vis
itors excellent; and although uneducated, Mrs. Eng
displayed much good sense and shrewdness in her
conversation.
On paying a visit to the twins themselves, at the
plantation in Surry, they were found engaged in j
shingling a house, lhe indoor arrangements ot Mrs. j
unang, pronounceu cuuu,; were more uwwiui man
those of her sister as she also excelled the latter in j
point of personal beauty. She has also three children; I
the eldest of whom, rejoicing in the' name of Josephine j
V irgima, is six aays younger man mrs. rmg s nrei i
born, i lie next cmia, inow mat we nave come to
these particulars,) was eight days younger than her
sister's second daughter and there was about the
same discrepancy (so to speak) in the ages of the
younger, doubly cousins. As to personal appearance,
the children were all much alike.
The twins seemed to be very happy; said they
liked farming very much, ln regard to politics, they
were decided Clay men and would like to vote for
him for President, as they expressed it if he (Mr. j
Clay,) 44 would let them." Their religious views j
embrace the Eastern doctrine of transmigration of
souls. They believe, on their death, they (we give
their own simple words) 44 go in hog first, and stay
until we repent for de bad in dis world den we go</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85026466/1852-12-08/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>THE SIAMESE TWINS.
Many persons who, in days gone by, have ta
ken a lively interest in tho welfare of Messrs.
Eng and Chang Bunkers, the celebrated Siam
ese twins may be glad to learn that those gen
tleraan are well and live at Mount Airy in N.
Carolina surrounded by their wives and chil
dren,
Mr. Eng has sir, and Mr. Chang five children,
all of whom are apt scholars and remarkably
well behaved manifesting the strongest possi
ble desire to learn their lessons and to secure
the good will of their teacher. They all par
take strongly of tho most refined Siamese cast
of countenance, form and manner of deporting
themselves in truth they are a credit to their
parents, and the community in which they live.
Formerly they lived in Wilkes county, but in
consequence of the numerous actions for as
sault and battery brought against them in the
county they removed into tho adjoining coun
ty, shortly after which they were fined fifteen
dollars and costs at Rockford, the county seat,
for splitting a board into splinters over the
head of a man who had insulted them.
As regards tho supposed sympathy existing
between them, it may be stated that their most
intimate acquaintances deem them to be entire
ly independent of every thing of the kind, and
give us instances to sustain their opinion, that
not long since they attended an auction sale of
hogs and bid against each other tnl they ran up
the prices altogether above the market rates
also, that on one occasion Mr. Eng or Chang
was taken ill and took to his bed where he lay
complaining for some time, although his broth
er scolded him severely all the winie lor aeiain
ing him in bed when he ought to have been at
tending to the business on the plantation.
On another occasion, as they were passing
up tho road, a gentleman enquired of them
where thev were going, whereupon Mr. Chang
replied 44 1 am a going over tho Bluo Ridge in
the stage," and at the same time Mr. Eng, look
ing over his shoulder, replied, with an arch smile
1 am going home to look after our wives and
children." When questioned about their moth
er some time since by an acquaintance they sta
ted that they had formerly received letters Irom
her, but latterly they had heard no tidings of
her and even if they wero to receive letters
from her written in the Siamese language, they
would not be able to read them, as they had for
gotten their mother tongue.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83035101/1853-04-27/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>The Siamese Twins.
Chang and Eng have started on an exhibition
through the United States, and were in New York,
on Saturday, on their way to Boston. They were
exhibited very generally a dozen years ago, made
a handsome fortune, and then settled as planters
in North Carolina. They married sisters, and as
the twins were bound together by indissoluble
bonds, they became heads of a double household.
In noticing the recent visit of Chang and Eng to
the N. Y. Herald establishment, that paper. says:
They purchased a plantation of some five hun
dred acres in the native State of their better halves
(North Carolina,) where they have been increas
ing and multiplying in family, men servants and
maid servants, and all material wealth. They
now possess an establishment of thirty slaves,
and a family of eleven children, of whom six are
referable to Chang and the other five to Eng.
They attend very industriously to the business of
their plantation kept the negroes to their work
were always ready and willing to turn their own
hands to something useful, and would plow, and
reap, and grind, and chop wood, and do all sorts of
farm work. Then when business was not urgent,
ihey would devote their time to field sports, and
were among the keenest hunters, fowlers and
fishermen of their district. In fact, they live as
real country gentlemen, ready to drink a. glass,
or fight a round, as occasion required.
The Mesdamese Chang and Eng seconded their
lords right well in the management of the con
cern, and have remained behind to take charge of
the household during the absence of their distin
guished consorts, Madame Chang devotes her
time to the general supervision of the slaves and
the direction of the work to be performed on the
plantation, while Madame Eng charges herself
with the care of the young masters and misses,
and keeps a school for their tuition and that of the
negroes'. We should not say all the children,
for. two of them accompany their sires in their
tour; and will doubtless, contribute much to the
interest with which they will be regarded where
ever they go.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85052141/1868-07-18/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>SIAMESE TWINS TO E SEPARATED
BT A SURGICAL OfSRATION.
The New York Tribune says, The
ientiSc worldT and especially that por-
f it who have made the study of
xneariue ana swreery tneir protession.

cannot 'Nil to be intensely interested in
the fact isvfcrh has recently come to our
knowledge cx.the determination of Eng
and Chang, the Siamese twins, to submit
to a surgical opera ti en for the purpose of
dissevering the wonderful link that has
so long bound them together. Some
forty years ego these twins were intro
duced to the notice of the civilized world,
having been brought to England from
Siam in the year 1827 or 1828, by Capt.
Bunker, at present living in New York,
and for a 6eries of years they were ex
hibited to the public at the great centers
of civilization. Llaving visited America,
they determined to make this land their
home. They bought a valuable tract of
land in North Carolina, married two
flfters, and settled down in the ordinary
routine of a farmer's daily life. Each of
them is now the father of nine children.
The reason for their determination, at
this late day, to call in the art of surgery
to produce an entire physical separation,
is, that having reached such an advanced
age (fifty -nine years) they are fearful
that one may become the subject of dis
ease, which may prove fatal to both. The
interesting question arises, What are the
probabilities of a successful operation
being perforated? It will be remember
ed in pursuvg these inquiries that the
twins arfheld together by a massive
link of 'thoroughly normal and perfectly
tritaled integument, some ten or twelve
es in cycumicrence, situatca near
e vital organs, and in close proximity
to the heart and lang3 and the connec
tion is so intimate that each seems to be
thoroughly an organized portion of the
other, as much so as any of the ordinary
members of a naturally constituted hu
man body. Sensation, nervous impres
eioc, mental phenomena, morbid, pbysi
cal, and nervomental conditions, all show
a most perfect psychiesl unity io this
wonderful dual physical existence. The
question in regard to the result of an
operation is no new one, but soon after
their first appcarauce in London and
Faris it excited the minds of the fore
most intellects ia the furgical world. If
we remember rightly the Twins were
exhibited before the Academy of Physi-
ana and Surgeons ia Paris at that time
the purr-ote cf ascertaining their
'fn ia regard to, the probabilities
successful operation-. The dis-
agreement</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85033673/1869-03-16/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Surgical+Examination+Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>urgieal Examination of the Biam.se
Twins.
From the London Star.
Sir James Simpson, the Profeisor of
Medicine and Midwifery in the Univer
sily of Edinburgh, has examined very
minutely and from every point of scien
tific interest these twins, and has deliv
ered a lecture to the students of the
University Class on these and other
recorded casee of nnitsd twins, of whom
they are in many respects the most re
markable on record. In this lecture,
which he publishes in the British Medi
cal Journal, he gives first their history
and description. Chang aid Eng, or, as
thev now sien themselves. Chang and
Eng Booker, are now forty -eight years of
age. They were two ot severaJ children
tbe rest being naturally formed. When
infants tbey were attached face to face,
but instinctive efforts from the earliest
age have so far elongated the bund as to
enable them to adopt an impertettt lateral
relation to each other. They are short,
but wirv-lookine men: Eng. the taller of
tbe two, bsiogooly five feet two and a half
tachos, (JbaDg, an inch shorter, ihey nse
the outer more than inner legs, by stand
ing. and tbeso are the larger in circum
ference. There is no inversion of posi
tion of the heart aod other organs,
Professor Allen Thomyson, of Glasgow,
has shown to be tbe general law in reia
tion to united twins. Neither of the res
pirations nor circulations of the two
brothers are synchronous. Examined
in Edinburgh by Dr. Aitken, when they
were suffering from is fluenza, tbe pulse
of one was twenty-lour beats to the
minute quicker than the other. Exam
ined in London by Sir Henry Thomp
son and Mr. Earnest Hart, there was less
difference four pulsations in the min
ute. In their chemical as well as their
organio functions, they are shown by Sir
James Simpson to be two separate and
di.tinct individuals. They can walk,
swim and run; they are keen sportsmen
and good shots; intelligent, well in
formed, and good men of business They
are naturally much accustomed to join in
the same conversation, but can each
easily carry on a conversation with two
different iadividuals. They sometimes
read separately, each to himself; more
often one aloud to the other. Their
minds, indeed, are more dual, than
their bodies the latter are united
together, but the former are not.
The band of anion is formed partly by
ibe extension of the cartilages of tbe
breastbones; it is four inches and a
half long, and eight inches and a half in
circumference. When the twins have
suflered from blood diseases, as small
pox, measles, ague, tbey have been
affected simultaneously. Nevertheless,
from experiments which Sir James
Simpson has made with drags, he con
cludes that tbe vascular connexion be
tween the two brothers is comparatively
small. Oa the question of the surgical
separation of the Siamese Twins, "Chang
and Eng," ssys Sir James Simpson,
"have themselves no desire to be surgi
cally divided from each other. Bat some
of their relatives and families have be
come asutious that tbey should be sepa
rated, if it were possible to do so. The
operation is possible, aod would be at
tended .with little or no difficulty;
Knt it would bo so perilous in its char-
acter that the twins could not, ia my
opinion.be jus'.ified in submitting to it,
er any surgeon justified in performing
it." He then enters into details to justify
this opinion. Chang end Eog are mar
ried to two sisters, the daughters of an
American clergyman. Each brother has
nice childreo. The familv of Eog con
sists of six sons and three daughters the
family of Chang consists of three sons
and six daughters. Their first children
were bora within three or four days of
each other; the oibers at irregular inter
val.. Chang's ninth child was bora three
months ago.
Sir W. Fergusson bas carefully exam
ined the twins, and, we understand, con
curs in the general opinion of surgeons
that any surgical separation would be
moat likely attended with fatal conse
quence, not so much on account of any
obstacle presented by the structure of the
uniting band of flesh, as the moral effect
of the disunion on the two brothers.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87056248/1869-07-29/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Personal+Habits+Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>Personal Habits of the Siamese Twins.
BV MARK TWAIN.
I do not wish to write of the personal
habit of these strange creatures solely,
but also of certain curious details of va
rious kinds concerning them, which, be
longing only to their private life, have
never crept into print. Knowing the
Twins intimately, I feel that I am pecu
liarly well qualified for the task I have
taken upon myself.
The Siamese Twins are naturally tender
and affectionate in disposition, and have
clung to each other with singular fidelity
throughout a long and eventful life. Eveu
as children they were inseparable com
panions and it was noticed that they al
ways seemed to prefer each other's society
to that of any other person's. They nearly
always played together and, so accus
tomed was their mother to this peculiarity,
that, whenever both of them chanced t
be lost, uhe usually only hunted for one
of them satisfied that when she found
that one she would find his brother some
where in the immediate neighborhood
And yet these creatures were ignorant
and unlettered barbarians themselves
and the offspring of barbarians, who knew
not the light of philosophy and science.
What a withering rebuke is this to our
boasted civilization, with its quarrelings,
its wranglings, and its separations of
brothers
As men, the Twins have not always
lived in perfect accord but, still, there
has always been a bond between them
wnicn maae tnem unwining to go away
lrom each other and dwell
apart. I hey
d a. S 9
h "ever failed to even sleep together
on any night since they were born.
How surely do the habits of a
lifetime become second nature to us The
Twins always go to bed at the smie time
but Chang usually gets up an hour before
his brother. By an understanding be
tween themselves, Chang does all the in
door work and Eng runs all the errands.
This is because Eng likes to go out
Chang's habits are sedentary. However,
Chang always goes along. Eng i9 a
Baptist, but Chang is a Roman Catholic
still, to please his brother, Chang consent
ed to be baptized at the same time that
Eng was, on condition that it should not
44 count." During the war they were
strong partisans, and both fought gallant
ly all through the great struggle Eng on
the Union side and Chang on the Con
federate. They took each other prisoners
at 8even Oaks, but the proofs of capture
were so evenly balanced in favor ot each
that a general army court had to be as
sembled to determine which one was prop
erly the captor and which the captive.
The jury was unable to agree for a long
time but the vexed question was finally
decided by agreeing to consider them both
prisoners, and then exchanging them. At
one time Chang was convicted of disobedi
ence of orders, and sentenced to ten days
in the guard house but Eng, in spite of all
arguments, felt obliged to share his im
prisonment, notwithstanding be himself
was entirely innocent and so, to save the
blameless brother fromsuflering, they had
to discharge both from custody the just
reward of faithfulness.
Upon one occasion the brothers fell out
about something, and Chang knocked
Eng down, and then tripped and fell on
him, whereupon both clinched and began
to beat and gouge each other without
mercy. The bystanders interfered and tried
to separate them, but they could not do
it, and so allowed them to fight it out. In
the end both were disabled, and were car
ried to the hospital on one and the same
shutter.
Their ancient habit of going always to
gether had its drawbacks when they
reached man's estate and entered upon the
luxury of courting. Both fell in love with
the same girl. Each tried to steal clandes
tine interviews with her, but at the critic
al moment the other would always turn up
By and by Eng saw, with distraction, that
(hang had won the girls anections and,
from that day forth, he had to bear with
the agony ot being a witness to all their
dainty billing and cooincr. Bnt, with a
magnanimity that did him infinite cred
it, he succumbed to his fate, and gave
countenance and encouragement to a state
of things that bade fair to sunder his gen
erous heart-strings. He sat from seven
every evening until two in the morning
listening to the fond foolishness of the two
lovers, and to the concussion of hundreds
of squandered kisses for the privilege of
sharing only one of which he wnuld have
given his right hand. But be sat patiently,
and waited, and gaped, and yawned, and
stretched, and longed for two o'clock
to come. And he took long walks
with the lovers on moonlight evenings
sometimes traversing ten miles, nolwith
standing he was usually suffering from
rheumatism. He was an inveterate
smoker but he could not smoke on these
occasions, because the young lady was
painfully sensitive to the smell of tobacco.
Eng cordially wanted them married, and
done with it; but, although Chang often
asked the momentous iptestion, the young
lady could not gather sufficient courage to
answer It while Eng was by. However,
on one occasion after hnving walked some
sixteen miUs.andsai uptillm a-ly daylight,
Eng dropped asleep from sheer exhaustion,
and then the question was asked and an
wered. The lovers were married. All ac
quainted with thecircumstancesapplaudvd
the noble brother-in law. Hlsunwavenng
faithfulness was the theme of every
tongue. He had staid by them all through
their long and arduous courtship and
when at last they were married, he lifted
his hands above their heads, and said
with impressive unction, 44 Bless ye, my
children, I will never desert ye and be
kept his word. Magnanimity like this is
all too rare in this cold world.
By and-bye Erg fell in love with his sis
ter in law's sister, and married her, and
since that day they have all lived together,
night and day, in an exceeding sociabil-
t i-i 1- .1 1 ilA.I 1...
ity which is touching and beautiful to be-
hold, and is a scathing rebuke to our boast
ed civilization.
The sympathy existing between these
two brothers is so close and so refined that
the feelings, the impulses, the emotions
oiineoneare instanUy experienced bv
the other. When one Is sick, the other is
sick when one feels oain. the other feels
n; when one is antjered, the other s tern
per takes fire. We have already seen
with what hanov facility thev both fell in
love with the same girl. Now, Chang is
mueriy opposed to all torms of intemper
ance, on principle but Eng is the reverse
lor, wniie these men s feelings and emo
tions are so closelv wedded, their reason
ing faculties are unfettered their thoughts
are iree. unang belongs to the Good
Templars, and is a hard-working and en
thusiastic supporter of all temperance re
forms. But. to his bitter distress, everv
now and then Eng gets drunk, and, of
course, mat makes Uhang drunk too. This
unfortunate thing has been a great sorrow
to Chang, for it almost destroys his useful
ness in his favorite field of effort. As
sure as he is to head a great temperance
procession Eng ranges up alongside of
him, prompt to the minute and drunk as
a lord but yet no more dismally and
hopelessly drunk than his brother who
has not lasted a drop. And so the two be
gin to hoot and yell, and throw mud and
bricks at the Good Templars, and,
of course, they break up the procession.
It would be manifestly wrong to punish
Chang for what Eug does, and, therefore,
the Good Templars accept the unto
ward situation, and suffer in silence and
sorrow. They have officially and deliber
ately examined into the matter, and find
Chang blameless. They have taken the
two brothers and filled Chang full of
warm water and sugar and Eng full of whis
ky, and in twenty-five minutes it was
not possible to tell which was the drunk
est. Both were as drunk as loons and
on hot whisky punches, by the smell of
their breath. Yet all the while Chang's
moral principles were unsullied, his con
science clear and so all just men were
forced to confess that he wa9 not morally,
but only physically drunk. By every
right and by every moral evidence the
man was strictly sober and, therefore, it
caused his friends all the more anguish to
see him shake hands with the pump and
try to m ind his watch with his night-key.
There is a moral in these solemn warn
ingsor, at leapt, a warning in these sol
emn morals one or the other. No mat
ter, it is somehow. Let us heed it let us
profit by it.
I could say more of an instructive na
ture about these interesting beings, but
let what I have written suffice.
Having forgotten to mention it sooner,
I will remark, in conclusion, that the ages
of the Siamese Twin9 are respectively
tifty-one and fifty-three years.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026965/1874-01-29/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Celebrated+Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>Death of the Celebrated Siamese Twins.
A correspondent of the New York Herald
furnishes the following particulars of the recent
death of Chang and Eng, the famous Siamese
Twins, which will be found exceedingly inter?
esting
Richmond, Va., Jan. 19, 1874.
A despatch from Greonsboro, N. C, gives the
startling announcement of the sudden death
of the celebrated Siamese Twins on Saturday
morning last, the 17th inst., which occurred at
their residence at Mount Airy, Surry county,
N. C.
There are no details of this sad event further
than the fact that Chang was partially paralyzed
last fall, since which time he had been fretful,
very much debilitated and strongly addicted to
drinking liquor as a means of alleviating his
suffering. He had been quite feeble for several
days?indeed so much so as to confine both the
brothers to bed, but the illness was not so gre?t
as to cause any anticipation of the catastrophe
that was to follow. On Friday night they re?
tired to bed as usual, but during the night
Chang became worse, and to the utter dismay
of all his friends, expired suddenly about four
o'clock on Saturday morning.
As soon as it was discovered that his spirit
had left its earthly tenement, and that death
had claimed him for his own, Eng became so
terribly shocked that he raved wildly for a
while, at times exhibiting signs of great men?
tal aberration. This attack was followed by
what seemed to be a deadly stupor, and all now
watched eagerly the fate of the surviving twin,
so long and inseparably united to his now dead
brother. In two hours, it is supposed, from
the death of Chang, Eng breathed his last, and
in dea-n, as in life, the souls, as well as the
bodies, of the celebrated twins were once more
reunited.
The wives and families of the twins are in
the deepest grief?the children, many of whom
are deaf mutes, expressing their sorrow and
bereavement in the most pitiful manner.
Greexsroro, N. C, Jan. 20, 1S74.
There is little additional intelligence from
Mount Airy, the late home of the deceased
Siamese Twins. That village is distant from
this point about eighty miles, and there is
neither telegraphic nor mail communication
with it. Reports that have reached here con?
firm the information given in the despatch^
from Richmond yesterday. A late arrival here
from Mount Airy states "that it was about six
o'clock in the morning on Saturday when ono
of the sons of the Twins, who slept up stairs,
heard a cry or call of alarm. The boy at once
repaired to the sleeping room of the Twins,
where he found Eng in a ver3T perturbed and
excited condition, the cause being the death of
his brother. After this, and as soon as the
death becamo generally known among the
members of the family, Eng grew worse until
dissolution followed, his only remark being,
"I suppose I must die, too."" In exactly two
hours his fears proved only too correct, and he
had departed this life. It is not known whether
the funeral has yet taken place, but tho suppo?
sition is that it has not. One report says that
it was to have taken place yesterday but this I
is not regarded as authentic.
It is stated that the family physician and oth?
er medical men who were present soon after I
the demise of the brothers, desired to dissever
the ligature or membrane that so effectually I
united them while living, for the purpose of as?
certaining if the death of Eng had beon pro?
duced by some vital artery passing through it,
but to this the family strongly objected It is
also reported that there is a provision in the
wills of the deceased twins against such uu
operation. Notwithstanding this, however, it
is hoped that in the interest of surgical science
and tor the benefit of the human race a post?
mortem examination will be held with a view
to solve the problem so long a mystery, which
is, had the ligature been operated upon during
life to separate the brothers would that opera?
tion have been followed by fatal results? In
their several tours through Europe the twins
wero examined by all tho leading surgeons at
each capital, none of whom ever attempted to
perform an operation upon this singular con?
nection.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1874-02-21/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Rumbilical+Twins+Siamese+Conjoined+Chang+Eng+Bunker</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>TBI RCMBILICAL TWINS.
Cbarg and Kng were gallant twins
Discovered in Siam,
And Eng grew up at Sabbath school,
While Chang he loved a slam;
A gristly rivet joined the twain,
The which would not unscrew,
So pious Eng was always slain
When Chang got on a slew.
In politics Eng was a Whig,
And Chang a democrat,
And when they held an argument
It ended in a spat,
And often when the vote was close,
Atd both sides scored a brother.
The court decided, tira voce,
They must contest each other.
Poor Eng he loved a Quaker maid
Who would not roost with Changv,
Because he came to bed so druuk
And said his pravers so slangy;
They compromised, and took a pair,
And lived in great dejection,?
The brothers wanted a divorce.
'1 he fcistere a dissection.
And Eng he loved to sing a hymn,
And Chang to tight a chicken;
Whenever Eng exhorted Chang
He got a martyr's lick in';
If in the chnrch'Eng led liisclafis
'T would make an angel kick up,
To see the one with unction pray,
And t'other sleep and hiccup."
They called a hundred surgeons in
To pass the righteous sentence,
It 'twould be safe to take a knife
Ard cut their own acquaintance.
The Doctors ot their hyphen felt
And came.to this solution:
Twas an action 'twixt the Little Belt
And the navel Constitution.
At last Chang would not sleep at all,
So much he was a soaker,
And kept his brother sitting np
To while him at draw poker;
And whenhedied the wretch remarked;
"The Lord must raise our bodies?
And I shall have all Eng's reward,
And likewise all those toddies."
The ladies sold the frail remains
To serve a human mission;
The Doctors beat Sir Baruum oat
And gave an exhibition;
They found the belt a derrick was,
Two sacks?one thin, one thicker?
And Eng had bad to brace the beam,
While Chang contained the liquor.
Hence one remarked upon the chain
With gravity rabbinical,
That on one side, at least, the strain
Must be ascribed rambilical.
And so the oater verdict was
Put down with all sincerity:
Their fathers had been Siamese twins,
W ith such anlike posterity.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053223/1945-09-13/ed-1/?sp=3&q=siamese+twins+life</id>
<rel>0</rel>
<text></text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86072239/1922-03-30/ed-1/?sp=1&q=siamese+twins+life</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>Siamese Twins
“OnelnLife”;
Same In Death
CHICAGO, March 30.—Josepha
Blazek and Rosa Blazek, the
famous Siamese Twins, joined
together by a large ligament,
passed away early this morning,
Josepha’s death occurred first,
and her sister, after a few gasps,
followed in a few seconds. Their
hearts beat practically as one.
Physicians had declared that
in the event of the death of one,
the other would die immediately.
There was a good chance to
save Rosa’s life, the surgeons
said, by an operation, seperating
their bodies, but their brother,
Frank Blazek, refused to permit
it, he said, the Twins were as
one, mentally and physically, and
that the one remaining would be
miserable and find life unendur
able.</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1926-10-05/ed-1/?sp=17&q=siamese+twins+life</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>“Siamese Twins,” joined by a 6-inch link
of tissue, who are appearing at Keith’s
Theater this week, are healthy, happy,
normal girls. This photo shows they
don’t have to both sleep when only one
wants to read at night.
Girl Siamese Twins
Enjoy Life
Triumphing over a. cruel twist of
fate which bound their bodies to
gether by »n inseparable link,
jualsy and Viojet Hilton, the
Siamese twins new playing ,at
Kiith's Theater, have learned how
to be as contested with their
Strange lot as the average ydting
ladles of today. i
Aside from the six-inch link of
tissue which binds them together
near the base of the spine, these
girls, now 18 yfgrs old. are per-
normal, happy and more
than ordinarily good looking.
Xhe girls do not depend qpon the
freak es their birth, however, to
make their way in the world. They
aye full of energy and
and are naturany good entertain
ers, h
They play g saxophone with the
charm of a peppy Vassar girl. They
dance, laugh hnd sing and offer
the unusual thing of two flappers—
for they are ybung and old enough
to be called such —always together
and never quarrelling.
Although chaperoned on and off
the stage by, an experienced and
charming lady; they would probably
give a sfnlle to any young god that
crossed their path—just because
they qrs normal young ladies.
Thsre is no bone matter in the
connecting link that so securely
binds their two bodies- Muscular
tissue, nerves, arterial and spinal
connections, however. make them
as one. They move about freely
without handicap and enjoy living.
BlpOd circulates freely between
them, and possibly any contagious
disease would affect both. But if
you prick your hand or have a
tooth pulled the sensation of pain
qujckly travel* to the brain, and,
remember, they" ,qre two distinct
girls. One cou|d hive indigestion
Fight Disease</text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030431/1919-11-16/ed-1/?sp=71&q=siamese+twins+life</id>
<rel>0</rel>
<text></text>
</result>
<result>
<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1925-08-03/ed-1/?sp=17&q=siamese+twins+life</id>
<rel>1</rel>
<text>PALACE —“Siamese Twins,” “Night
Life of New York.”
j Special interest centers about the
Palace Theater this week, where
Violet and Daisy Hilton, “Siamese
twins" of San Antonio. Tex., are
making appearances four times daily.
Aside from the, natural interest that
these two girls, bound together at
birth, arouse, they offer an act that j
j has real entertainment value and dis-
I play talents that will compare favor
ably with people of normal develop
ment. Their first number is a saxo
phone duet, played with spirit and
precision. This is followed by a vocal
duet into which they inject excellent
close harmony. They finish with a
dance with partners in tandem style
that is quite remarkable. The girls,
who are now 16 years of age, are
pretty, gentle and refined in de
meanor and, aside from this trick of
Nature, which keeps them bound to
gether for life, seem quite like other
happy, normal girls. The “barker”
was the only part of the act that
might well have been left out.
The photoplay attraction is “Night
Life of New York,” in which Rod La
Roque and Dorothy Gish, the latter
making her first appearance for sev
eral months, are the principal lumi
naries. It’s all about a young butter
and egg man from the West whose
rich “pop." recognizing the right that
j "youth must be served,”, sends his
1 son to New York to sew his proverbial
wild oats before settling down to the
business of life. This father, how
ever, whose own experiences in his
youth have left scars, arranges with
a wise old crony whereby the boy
shall see everything along the gay
white way, so that he will become
completely "fed up” and glad to get
back to the simplicity of his small
town home. To this end a sort of
professional charmer is engaged, un
known, of course, to the boy, and to
gether they take in exactly what the
title of the picture intimates. Some
thing goes wrong with the plans, how
ever. The boy falls for the wrong
girl, who, in time, turns out to be
the right girl and the “finis” finds
everybody happy in true movie style.
A short comedy, the weekly news
shots and orchestral music complete
the bill.</text>
</result>
</results>
</topic>
</topics>
